s
s
n
n
.
.
c
c
g
g
h
h
a
a
n
n
u
u
pull
pull
cut
cut
areas
areas
so
so
curbs
curbs
w
w
f
f
n
n
w
w
o
o
2018 Governor's Banquet, Science Popularization Lectures and Speakers in October
2018年知事响宴 10月份科普讲座演长会开始
We ask the Director of No Impulse of the Secretariat of the Court to host for us
我们请本院秘书处无冲力处长为我们主持
Okay, thank you all colleagues present
好 谢谢在场的各位同仁
Or interested in popular science
或者是对于科普有兴趣的
There is still a little drizzle outside in this early autumn season
在这个初秋的季节外头还有一点毛毛细雨
Still willing to take off the tired mood after a day of work
还愿意在工作了一天脱着疲惫的心情
I am also willing to come to the Institute of Chinese Studies to listen to lectures on popular science
还愿意来到中文研究院来听科普的讲座
Today's speech is given by the deputy director of our Institute of Astronomy and Astrophysics
今天的演讲是由我们天文及天文物理研究所的副所长
Researcher Wang Xiangyu, who is also the deputy director
王祥宇研究员 他本身也是副所长
he came to give a keynote speech
他来进行一个主题演讲
The eyes of astronomers who make astronomers
叫做打造天文学者的天文学家的火眼津津
The development of Jianduan astronomy
剪端天文一气的开发
What about Mr. Wang, he and I are in fact the black hole this time
王老师呢 我跟他其实这次的黑洞
because of the black hole
因为黑洞的关系
So have more close interaction with him
所以跟他有更多的密切的互动
He is a very personable, very gentle person
他是一个非常个性 非常温潤的一个人
I took a closer look at his profile
我仔细看了一下他的资料
He himself graduated from the Institute of Electronics of our Jiaotong University
他本身是毕业我们交通大学的电子研究所
After he graduated with a Ph.D.
他在博士毕业了之后
joined our newly established
就加入了我们那个时候刚成立的
Astronomical Institute of Astrophysics
天文级天文物理研究所
Currently a researcher and deputy director of our astronomical institute
目前是我们天文所的研究员兼副所长
he is central university
他是中央大学
He is also an adjunct professor at the Central Space Science Institute
同时也是中央太空科学研究所的兼任教授
and director of the East Asia Observatory
以及东亚天文台的董事
His research specialization was developed in Astronomical Rituals
他的研究专场是在天文仪式开发
small solar system bodies
还有太阳系小天体
Infrared detection
红外线的侦测
dendrite gold
还有分子树磊金
The teacher told me that I don't know what astronomical Shulei gold is
老师讲我不知道什么叫天文树磊金
his research looks real
他的研究看起来是真的
really great
真的很厉害
It is currently the only one in the astronomical institute
它是目前天文所裡頭唯一一味
Personnel who can engage in the development of visible light and infrared rays
可以從事可見光和紅外線一系開發的人員
Dominated four international telescopes over the years
這些年來主導了四個國際望遠鏡的
Instrument R&D Equipment
儀器的研發設備
It is also a Sino-US acting project
也是中美演精計畫
And one of the hosts of the Neptune Celestial Show Mind Project
還有海王星天體演心計畫的一個主持人
It conducts research on the evolution history of the solar system
它進行的是有關於太陽系的演化歷史的研究
At the same time participated in the research and development of Japanese scientific satellites
同時參與了日本科學衛星的研發
Also completed research globe
也完成了研究地球儀
Electron Analyzer of the Magnetosphere
磁層的電子分析儀
To be fair I don't even know what that means.
持平來講我都不知道這是什麼意思
But we may ask Mr. Wang to explain later
不過我們等一下可能會請王老師說明一下
it is currently leading a team
它目前正在帶領一個團隊
Entering the Next Generation of Infrared Space Telescopes
進入到下一個世代的紅外線太空望遠鏡
and the future world's largest
以及未來全世界最大的
Instrument development for the European Visible Light Telescope
歐洲可見光的望遠鏡的儀器開發
And hope to expand Taiwan astronomy
而且希望能夠拓展台灣天文
Opportunity to participate in state-of-the-art observing equipment
參與最新觀測設備的機會
It also assists domestic manufacturers
也是協助國內的廠商
Build an automated large area detector
建立自動化大面積偵測器
There is also a system for camera detection
還有相機偵測的一個系統
Hopefully these astronomical instruments will resolve
希望這些天文儀器能夠解決
It's not just about seeing the sky
它不只是能夠看天象
It can also solve our current domestic industry
還能夠解決我們目前國內產業
domestic and foreign industries
就是國內外產業界
all the problems
所有所面臨到的問題
and create some possible business opportunities
還有創造一些可能的商機
It's a little bit windy outside today
今天外頭比較飄著
english fat
英語肥肥
But if you are interested
但是如果大家有興趣
I don't know everyone last Saturday
我不知道大家上個禮拜六
Have you ever come to see go away open
有沒有來看到遠去開放
Everyone can also go to the Humanities Museum
大家也可以到人文館的
the stairs
階梯那個地方
can see us a black hole
可以看到我們一個黑洞
This year is our Central Plains
今年就是我們中原
a very important year
一個非常重要的一年
Our team in Taiwan and the world
我們台灣跟世界的團隊
we found
我們共同發現
Black hole photographed for the first time
第一次拍到了黑洞
confirmed the black hole
證實了黑洞的
If you look carefully
大家如果仔細去看
It's actually very, very difficult
其實是非常非常不容易的事情
if you look at it now
如果你以現在的角度來說
that picture looks
那個畫面看起來
not very clear
還不是很清楚
Then I was last Saturday
那我在上個禮拜六
I just heard
我才聽到
How difficult is it to photograph that black hole?
要拍到那個黑洞的難度有多高
after everyone listened
大家聽了之後
I just discovered my admiration for that Teacher Wang
我才發現我對那個王老師的景仰
deep in my heart
心裡由然而深
how difficult that is
那個多困難
As you can imagine, it's probably from New York
大家想像大概就是從紐約
to see in los angeles
要看到在洛杉磯
a golf ball
的一個高爾夫球
a small groove on the top
上面的一個小的凹槽
You can imagine how difficult it would be
你可以想像這個難度會有多高
So it's no wonder we're developing everything so cutting-edge
所以無怪乎我們要發展這麼尖端的一切
So let me think about it
所以我再大家想想看
Seeing Los Angeles from New York
從紐約看到洛杉磯
A small groove in a golf ball
一個高爾夫球裡頭的小凹槽
how did it work
到底怎麼辦到的
Next, we warmly welcome Mr. Wang
接下來我們就熱烈歡迎王老師
Come help us analyze
來幫我們解析一下
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you Director
謝謝處長
goodbye
再會
I've actually been playing this video before starting my talk
開始我的演講之前其實我一直在放這個影像
Then this is actually everyone's image
那這個其實就是大家的影像
I use this little machine
我用這個小小的機器
This is the instrument we developed ourselves
這個就是我們自己開發的儀器
But in fact, this is still far from most astronomical instruments.
但其實這個跟大部分的天文儀器還是差得很遠
This is the one we developed for Zhongshan Science people.
這個是我們幫中山科學人就願開發了一個
a new chair used on satellites
衛星上面使用的一個新項椅
it can do very fast tracking
它可以做很快的追蹤
Know the current attitude of my satellite
了解我衛星目前的姿態
The current attitude of artificial satellites is a thing for navigation
人造衛星目前的姿態來做導航的一個東西
Then I want to use this small example to tell you
那我是想要用這個小小的例子來跟大家講說
In addition to astronomical instruments
除了天文儀器之外
In fact, there are many other related applications
其實還有做很多其他相關的應用
Then I will start my speech today
接下來我就開始我今天的演講
Director Wu just introduced the topic of today's speech
那剛剛吳處長有介紹今天演講的題目就是
introduce everyone
介紹大家
Have some knowledge about the astronomical instruments behind the development of it
有關於天文儀器開發它的背後的一些知識
Where is its application and its difficulty
它的應用 它的困難度在哪裡
in this first page
在這個第一頁裡面
In fact, I put a picture of the moon
其實我就放了一個月亮的照片
This photo of the moon was actually taken by my daughter
這個月亮照片其實是我女兒拍的
She took a digital camera
她就拿了一個數位相機
It's the fried moon
就是炒的月亮
just push it down
就把它按下去
Then you will see full image
然後你就會看到滿好影像
In fact, the current technology is honestly very advanced.
其實現在的科技老實說真的滿發達的
So in fact, many times
所以其實在很多時候
If you are looking for a place to construct a case
你如果找一個構案的地方
You go to the right place in the sky to shoot
你去超天空對的地方拍
you can shoot this
你就可以拍到這個
It's still a very beautiful image of the Milky Way
還算是非常漂亮的這個銀河影像
then you may think
那大家可能會想
Hey, since you can just go and buy a digital camera
欸 那你既然就可以去隨便買一個數位相機
You just shot it so well
你就拍出來就這麼棒了
So why do you want the school to do it yourself?
那求你學校幹嘛還要自己做
I'll just go around and find someone to get my equipment out.
我就到處去找人家把我的儀器弄出來就好
that's actually
那實際上就是
I also said today that I hope that after listening to
我今天也講希望大家聽完之後
just talk about why
就可以聊說欸 為什麼
We have to spend so much effort on the development of astronomical instruments
我們要花這麼大的力氣去做天文儀器的開發
Mainly there are very main reasons why we have to do it ourselves
主要有非常主要的原因,為什麼我們要自己做
It's just that you can't buy it
就是其實都是買不到
Because you can find these cameras in the market
因為大家市面上可以找到這些相機
or imaging systems, in fact, they are all fixed specifications
或是成像系統,其實他們都是固定的規格
But we astronomers special binoculars
可是我們天文學家專用的望眼鏡
In fact, they all have different designs
其實它都有不同的設計
So each binocular has its own characteristics
所以每個望眼鏡都有它自己的特性
kind of like your own eyes
就有點像你自己的眼睛一樣
If everyone's eyes are short-sighted
每個人眼睛如果近視的時候
You can't wear someone else's glasses
你不能把別人眼鏡拿來戴
so i can see clearly
這樣我就會看得清楚
The same goes for every binocular, it has its own designed focal length
每個望眼鏡也是一樣,它有它自己的設計的焦距
In addition to this focal length, it has the so-called phase difference in the system
除了這焦距之外,它有所謂的系統裡面的相差
so it's hard for you to get between binoculars
所以你很難在望眼鏡之間
I'm the one who moves this department around
就是我把這一系搬來搬去
you can get the same effect
就可以得到一樣的效果
In addition, in fact, every binocular
另外就是說,其實每一個望眼鏡
it all wants to have its own character
它都想要有自己的特性
Make the best science in the world
做出世界最好的科學
So I'm going to achieve the best of this
所以我要達到最好的這個
We speak the words of the best potency
我們說最好的效能的話
then i will do it myself
那我就要自己來做
Of course, another reason is that
那當然另外的原因就是說
In fact, if you are really rich
其實你如果真的很有錢的話
You can definitely find Guangshi to do it for you
你一定可以找到光氏幫你做
It's just that most scientists are really poor
只是大部分科學家真的是滿窮的
Our funds are usually picked again and again.
我們的經費通常都是一摳再摳
So everyone becomes self-developed
所以大家都變成自己自行研發
Then let the research of this astronomy department
那這裡就讓這個天文系的研究
become a very special field of study
變成是一個很特別的一個研究的領域
In fact, the whole world
其實整個世界來說
The person engaged in the development of the first phase of this astronomy
從事這個天文一期開發的人
Maybe it's because we've been in touch so often
可能大概我們這樣常常接觸
probably a few thousand
大概就是幾千位
so it's not a huge area of ​​research
所以它並不是一個很大的研究領域
But it is for the study of astronomy
但是它對於天文的研究
is a very big contribution
是有非常大的貢獻
then this is a photo
那這個是一張照片
Here's a picture of me taking this thing apart
這就是我把這個東西分解開來的照片
actually tell you
其實就是告訴你說
Presumably there will be something inside an instrument
大概在一個儀器裡面會有什麼東西
I will introduce it in detail later
我等一下會再仔細的介紹
that this thing because it's small
那這個東西因為它很小
This is about the smallest thing we've ever made that could easily be brought here
這是大概是我們做過最小的東西可以很容易拿來這裡
Basically, the instrument we developed is a big thing
我們基本上我們開發的這個儀器都是磅岸大物
It's also very heavy, weighing several tons
也是非常重,重達了好幾噸
I can't bring it here for everyone to see
我沒有辦法把它拿來這邊給大家觀賞
The main reason why it is necessary to make such a big thing
那主要的原因為什麼會需要做這個磅岸大物
In fact, it has a lot to do with the progress of our human technology.
其實就是跟這個我們人類科技的進步有很大的關係
Then everyone may be familiar with it
那大家可能都很耳熟能想
We are famous in Taiwan for the manufacture of this semiconductor
我們在台灣很有名就是這個半導體的製造
There is a well-known motorcycle listening rate in semiconductor manufacturing to tell you
半導體的製造裡面就有一個很有名的摩托聽率告訴你
That is to say, the same area of ​​these chips can carry the number of transistors
就是說這些晶片它裡面同樣的面積可以承載的這個電晶體的數目
In fact, its increasing speed is a logarithmic increase in terms of time.
其實它的增加的速度對時間來講它是一個對數的增加
Then this law is also applicable if you put it into the astronomy
那這個定律你把它放到天文的這個磅岸進來說也是適用
Everyone should know that
大家應該知道就是
GID slightly 400 years ago
GID略在400年前
He was the first person to invent net access
他是第一個發明網進的人
What was the caliber of the net inlet he invented 400 years ago?
那400年前他發明網進的口徑多少
is only 2 cm
就是只有2公分
that passed 400 years
那經過了400年
right now we
我們現在
Visible light network entrance with the largest aperture
最大口徑的可見光網進
is 10 meters
就是10公尺
maybe later
那大概再過
It's 2019
現在是2019年
In about five or six years
大概再過個五六年
There will be one in Europe
歐洲就會出現一個
Nearly 40 meters net net entry
接近40公尺的網網進
then this is a
那這個是一個
a very rapidly growing curve
非常快速增長的一個曲線
So with this astronomical
所以隨著這個天文的
The caliber of this net becomes larger
這個網網進的口徑變大
Then the size of the instrument I need
那我需要的儀器的大小
will also get bigger and bigger
也會變得越來越大
Then you may find it a little strange to hear this.
那大家聽到這個可能會覺得有點奇怪
Really?
真的嗎?
The largest astronomical network
這個最大的天文網網進
is only 10 meters
是只有10公尺
We seem to be here all the time
我們好像常在這個
The explosives will see that China has an eye in the sky
爆裝者會看到說中國有一個天眼
This sky eye is a 500-meter location
這個天眼是500公尺的外景
But this because it is a
但這個因為它是一個
We say that it is suitable for locations with relatively long radio wave fields
我們說適用於無線電波場比較長的外景
it's not like what i just said
它並不像我剛剛講的
All the things I just said here
我剛剛講的這邊的所有的
All visible light
都是可見光的外景
Then your TRON range is different
那你波場的範圍不一樣
In fact, your application technology is also different.
其實你的應用道技術也就不一樣
So we're basically
所以我們現在基本上
We still have to use the same standard to compare
我們還是要用同樣的標準來比較
same technique
同樣的這個技術
That's what I was talking about
那其實剛我在講這個
When binoculars get bigger and bigger
望眼鏡的尺寸越來越大的時候
In fact, scientists still use some small tricks
其實科學家還是有用了一些小小的技巧
That this is the current world
那這個是目前世界上
arguably the most famous
可以說最有名的
This CAC binoculars from UC
加州大學的這個CAC望眼鏡
it's a 10 meter telescope
它是一個10公尺的望眼鏡
You can see that it is not a complete mirror
大家可以看到它並不是一個完整的鏡面
In fact, it has a large
它其實在它的鏡面上面是有很大的
A lot of hexagons put together
很多個六角形拼起來
That's because scientists are doing the research and development of the binoculars
那是因為科學家在做這個望眼鏡的研發過程
You slowly discovered that I have encountered a technical bottleneck
你慢慢發現說我已經遇到技術上面的瓶頸
If I put the same big single lens
我如果再把同樣一個大的單一的鏡片
while slowly expanding its size
慢慢一直擴張它的尺寸的時候
I will find it very difficult to make my
我會發現我的製作上面非常困難
Therefore, modern visible glasses usually use splicing technology
所以現代的可見望眼鏡通常都是用拼接的技術
Hexagonal binoculars about one meter in length
大概大約是一公尺左右的六角形的望眼鏡
put it together and form it into a larger binoculars
把它拼起來 把它形成一個比較大的望眼鏡
This picture shows the size of the largest binoculars in the world
這一個圖就是把目前世界上比較大的望眼鏡的大小
with its mirror image
跟它的鏡面的樣子
draw it all out
把它全部的把它畫出來
It can be found that in the early days, a single lens was used to form my binoculars
可以發現到在早期都是用單一鏡片來構成我的望眼鏡
That's about eight meters away.
那大概到了這個八公尺左右之間
we just stop doing this
我們就停止做這件事情
Therefore, all mirrors with a caliber exceeding 8 meters often use this splicing method.
所以超過8公尺口徑往往鏡全部都用這個拼接的方法
Use a small regular mirror to go back and forth
用小的往往鏡來去
Small lenses come and go to combine into one large lens
小的鏡片來去組合成一個大的鏡片
So next in
所以接下來在
In the next 10 years, I expect there will be 30-meter class
未來10年裡面我預期會有30公尺級的
Large astronomical mirrors tend to slowly
大型的天文往往鏡會慢慢的
Join the ranks of this astronomical observation
加入這個天文觀測的行列
Of course these observations
當然這些觀測
It requires very sophisticated astronomical instruments
它就需要有非常尖端的天文儀器
so that you can use
這樣才能夠使用
In order to really put the wide mouth mirror
才能真正把大口鏡的
Observation ability of the mirror
往往鏡的觀測能力
play it out
把它發揮出來
So advances in observational astronomy
所以觀測天文學的進步
In fact, it has a lot to do with the development of astronomical instruments.
其實它跟天文儀器的這個發展有很大的關聯性
On the contrary, if you can master the technology of these astronomical instruments
相反的你如果能夠掌握這些天文儀器的技術
you can master observation
你就可以掌握觀測
Suspect of the Department of Astronomy
上測天文系的嫌疾
So Central Academy of Astronomy
所以中央院天文所
we are at
我們在
When we established the institute more than 20 years ago, we
二十幾年前成所的時候我們就
Sure
確定
We are doing science at the same time
我們是同時會進行科學
research and development of the Department of Astronomy
研究還有天文一系的發展
that in the past twenty years
那在過去二十幾年間
We also put a lot of effort into
我們也花了很多力氣來
to develop
開發
and
跟
Improve our astronomy department
增進我們這個天文一系上面的
this ability
這個能力
Then I thought about our current
然後我想到現在我們的
Scientific achievements are similar to those of our astronomy department
科學成果跟我們天文一系的這個
developed this
發展的這個
result
結果
It can be said that it matches quite well.
可以說是搭配的相當的
pretty good
相當的良好
That
那
What exactly does an astronomy school want in general?
到底一般來說天文學校它想要的是什麼
Astronomy schools are actually
天文學校其實跟
Like most scientists
大部分科學家一樣就是
This signal is actually
這個訊號其實是
the more the merrier
越多越好
So it's better if I can
所以最好是我一次可以
collect all
收滿所有
from the universe
從宇宙間
able to reach the earth
能夠傳到地球
collect it all at once
一次都把它收集好
what does it mean to collect well
那一次收集好的意思是什麼
It doesn't matter which direction you come from
就是不管你是從哪個方向來啊
i can tell
我都可以知道說
when did you come to my earth
你是什麼時候到我地球
Then you come here and there are a few trees
然後你來到這邊有幾個樹木
Then I also know the energy of each photon
然後我還知道說每一個這個光子的能量
That is to say, I hope
也就是說我希望呢
I can do things that say
我能夠做到事情就是說
I have high resolution
我有很高的解析
spatial resolution
空間的解析度分
time resolution
還有時間的解析度
Then I can measure the light very accurately
然後我可以測光測得很準
And then there's also very high-resolution spectra at the same time
然後同時還有非常高解析度的光譜
just know
就知道說
Hey, this light is red
欸這個光是紅色
this light is blue
這個光是藍色
at different points in time
在不同的時間點
Each of these different colors of light
這個每一個不同顏色的光
how to hit earth
怎麼樣打到地球
like this image
就像這個影像
This is a
這是一個
First you make the image of Xingyun Neng 31
先你做星雲能31的影像
So of course astronomers want to say
所以天文學家當然希望說
I just need to take a picture
我只要一拍一個影像
I'm not only able to know the inside of this
我不僅僅是能夠知道這個裡面
how bright everything is
每一個東西多亮
I can still know
我還可以知道說
that goes with the matter
那隨著事情
what kind of change
是怎麼樣的變化
And what kind of this is in it
然後它裡面到底含有什麼樣的這個
gas or metal
氣體啊 或是金屬啊
or various elements like this
或是各種不同的元素這樣子
Of course, to achieve this is actually
當然要達到這個事情其實是
It's very, very difficult to be honest
老實說是非常非常的困難
Because we know the range of electromagnetic waves
因為我們知道電磁波的範圍
is very very big
是非常非常大的
is that it can be read from the radio
就是它可以從無線電
all the way to infrared all the way to our visible light
一直到紅外線一直到我們的可見光
then to UV
然後到紫外線
Then to X-ray or even this GaMaRay with shorter wavelength
然後到X-ray甚至波長更短的這個GaMaRay
Those electromagnetic waves of different wavelengths
那這些不同波長的電磁波
It brings us a different message
它帶給我們的是不同的訊息
That also means that it is correspondingly
那也代表它是相對應來說
Emitted by this celestial body with different temperatures
有不同溫度的這個天體所發出來的
What about the different electromagnetic waves?
那不同的這個電磁波呢
Because of its different characteristics
因為它的特性不一樣
So when you are going to collect these signals
所以你在要去收集這些訊號的時候
you have to use a different method
你就要用不同的方法
So although it is still ideal
所以雖然還理想上面
I want to say that if I have an ideal this
我是希望說我如果有一個理想的這個
I know this astronomical instrument once
這個天文儀器我一次就知道說
Hey, what is this calling in?
誒 這個打進來到底是
Gamma Ray or X-Ray or
Gamma Ray 或是 X-Ray 或是
Visible light or microwave signal
可見光或是微波的訊號
But actually this is
但實際上這個是
So far we have not been able to do this
這到目前為止我們是沒有辦法做到這件事情
So usually when we develop astronomical instruments,
所以通常我們在透過天文儀器的開發的時候
We'll take the band and separate it
我們就會把這個波段把它分開
For example, I mostly do
比如說我自己大部分是做
this band
這一個波段
Visible light and infrared
就是可見光跟紅外線
Then some people will do this high-energy
那有些人就是會做這個高能的
This detection of S light or Gamma Ray
S光或是 Gamma Ray 的這個偵測
that astronomical instrument it of course
那天文儀器它當然
After getting these data
在得到這些數據之後
it's basically doing analysis
它基本上在做分析的時候
I was just talking about different colors of light
我剛有談到不同顏色的光
It represents different substances
它代表的是不同物質
or different physical properties
或者是不同的物理性質
Different substances may be
不同物質可能就是
if i go and say
我如果去看說
A celestial body emits this spectrum
一個天體發出來這個光譜
There are some absorption lines in the spectrum
光譜裡面有一些吸收線
Then this absorption line is usually
那這個吸收線通常就是
It means that in my mind and body
就是代表說我這個心體裡面
or inside this cloud
或這個雲氣裡面
are specific to these molecules
是有特定的這些分子
Those molecules can make me
那這些分子可以讓我
can absorb this
可以吸收掉這個
This light that continuously emerges above
這個連續浮現上面的光
But continuous emergence also makes sense
但是連續浮現也有意義
The continuous emergence usually has this intensity distribution of its
那連續浮現通常它的這個強度分布
tell us yes
告訴我們是
The temperature of this celestial body
這個天體的溫度
what about besides this
那除了這個之外呢
of course i want
我當然是要
I have another method which is
我還有另外一個方法就是
I can go and get this whole full image
我可以去得到這個整個完整的影像
or smooth
或是光浮
The image can get the relative position
那影像可以得到相對的位置
every celestial body
就是每一個天體
Relatively warm position between
相對之間的溫的位置
then its brightness
然後它的亮度
Then follow its distribution
然後跟它的分布
Then these can sometimes tell us that
那這些可以有時候可以告訴我們說
do they belong to the same area
他們是不是屬於同一個區域的
celestial body
天體
Is there some between them
他們之間是不是有一些
The role of interaction
交互的作用
That light will show us the different substances
那光浮會告訴我們不同物質
its
它的
scalar size
純量的大小
or temperature
或是溫度
it even you can know it
它甚至你可以知道它
distance from our telescope
距離我們的遠鏡
Because different celestial bodies will have different displacements
因為不同的天體它會有不同的位移
Because of the Doppler effect
因為都普樂效應的關係
So from the spectrum we can see its distance
所以從光譜我們可以看到它的距離
Another possibility is that the light that can be excited by it
另外還有可能就是可以用它激化的光
the direction of its intensification can understand its various environments
它的激化的方向可以了解它處在各種不同的環境
And is there any magnetic field distribution near it?
還有它的附近是不是有磁場分布
Then this is NASA and there is a famous picture
那這個就是NASA還有一個很有名的圖片
It puts all of NASA's intensification
它就把所有的NASA的激化
This view of the entire Milky Way
所看到的整個銀河系的這個
Images at different wavelengths draw it
在不同的這個波長上面的影像把它畫出來
that can see the Milky Way from high energies all the way down to very low energies
那可以看到從高能量一直到很低能量的銀河系
it actually looks different
其實看起來都不一樣
That's why it's different, of course
那這不一樣的原因當然
Including whether there is something in it that it will absorb
包含說這裡面是不是有一些東西它會吸收掉
For example, in visible light, it has a lot of dust
比如說在可見光它就有很多灰塵
will absorb
會吸收掉
The signal is at a relatively high-energy position
訊號,在比較高能的這個位置
In fact, it can really emit this high-energy
其實真正能夠發出這個高能的
The source of the signal
訊號的這個訊號源
Relatively speaking, it is much less than visible light or infrared light.
相對來說也比可見光或是紅外線來的少很多
So scientists have to compare the different wavelengths
所以科學家要透過比較各個不同的波長
Detect this info for us
給我們偵測到這個資訊
I just managed to piece together the whole thing.
我才有辦法拼湊出整個完整的這個
celestial man, this image of celestial
天體的人,天體的這個圖像
or to fully know
或是才能完整的知道說
what happened to it in these places
到底在這些地方它發生了什麼事情
So what we just said, astronomers need to know
那我們剛剛講,天文學家需要知道
complete this entire electromagnetic wave this
完整的這個整個電磁波的這個
range of this message
範圍的這個訊息
But it's a pity we live on the earth
但是很可惜我們是住在地球上面
What about this earth?
那這個地球上面呢
One thing that is very important to us is the atmosphere
有一個對我們很重要的東西就是大氣神
As for the atmosphere, it is very important to human beings
那大氣神呢,對人類非常重要
We have to breathe every day, we need oxygen
我們每天都要呼吸,要有氧氣
In fact, he is...
事實上,他對...
What about humans?
人類來說呢
Of course, it also blocks a lot of things that are harmful to humans.
當然它也屏蔽掉很多這個對人類有害的這個
This very high energy electromagnetic wave
很高能量的這個電池波
Of course, for astronomical observations
當然對天文觀測來講
Does it block a lot
它等於是不是阻擋了很多
The signal that recently came from the universe to the ground
近來從宇宙近來到地面的這個訊號
So generally speaking, observations on the ground
所以一般來說在地面上的觀測呢
we only have three bands
我們只有三個波段
That's visible light, infrared, and radio.
就是可見光 紅外線 還有無線電
The signal of these three bands
這三個波段的這個訊號
We can make astronomical observations from the ground
我們可以在地面上進行天文的觀測
the lower part
那前下部分
Like most of this
比如說大部分的這個
X-ray or Gamma Ray
X光或是Gama Ray
or longer-wavelength infrared rays
或者是波長比較長的紅外線
We have to launch Sputnik
我們就必須要發射人造衛星
in order to see the impact
才有辦法看到這些影響
there is no way on the ground
在地面上就沒有辦法
Besides this effect
那除了這個影響之外呢
The atmosphere and the so-called atmospheric labor
那大氣還有所謂的大氣的勞動
what is that atmospheric labor
那大氣的勞動是什麼
Atmospheric labor is
大氣勞動就是
For example, when the weather is hot
比如說天氣很熱的時候
If you see no oil on the road
你如果看到不油路上面
There are often things like distorted images that appear
常常會有扭曲的影像這種東西出現
Then this is because of your atmosphere on the surface
那這個就是因為你在地表的大氣
its own uneven temperature
它本身溫度不均勻
If the temperature is uneven
那溫度不均勻的話
Its refractive index will be different
它的這個折射率就會不一樣
the light will be biased
光線就會偏著
Then the light is biased
那這個光線偏著
Usually when we look at the stars
通常我們在看星星的時候
that's what we used to sing when we were kids
就是我們常常小時候唱的
twinkle Twinkle Little Star
一閃一閃亮晶晶
That day is a little star
那一天都是小星星
that sparkle
那一閃閃亮晶晶
In fact, it is the astroman who hates the most
其實就是天文俠最恨
That twinkle twinkle sparkle sounds so
那一閃一閃亮晶晶晶聽起來很
seems very romantic
好像很浪漫
Actually it's very, very bad for Astroman
其實它是對天文俠非常非常的糟糕
because it
因為它
If you put this twinkle twinkle star
你如果把一閃一閃亮晶晶的這個星星
high speed video
把它有很高速的影像
It looks like this when you look at it
來看的話它就變這樣子
The star is actually running around all the time
就那星星其實它是一直跑來跑去
Then its point of light is not a
然後它的光點並不是一個
Not a fully focused spot of light
並不是一個完整對焦的光點
So this creates this point of light on this star
所以這造成了這個星星的這個光點
will be big
會很大
will be much larger than the optical quality we originally designed
會遠比它我們原本設計的光學品質要來的大
Then this deflection has the greatest effect on electromagnetic waves with shorter wavelengths
那這種偏摺對波長越短的電磁波影響最大
So on the ground because we can only see the shortest visible light
所以在地面上因為我們只能看到可見光最短
It's probably a little bit visible in ultraviolet light.
大概是紫外線可以看到一點點
So visible light has the greatest effect
所以可見光的影響最大
If it is electromagnetic waves like me, this is the image of a black hole
如果是電磁波像我這是黑洞那個影像
An electric shuttle with such a long wavelength cannot see this
波長那麼長的電梭它就看不到這個
So we can see images of black holes from the ground
所以我們可以在地面上看到黑洞影像
Also because it doesn't have this
也是因為它沒有這個
You can get such a high-resolution video
可以拿到那麼高解析錄影像
It is also because it does not have the relationship of atmospheric labor
也是因為它沒有這個大氣勞動的關係
The different wavelength ranges actually look very different
那不同的波長範圍一切其實它長得也很不一樣
this is
這個是
This is the visible light instrument that you are more likely to be more familiar with.
這是比較可能大家比較正可能比較大家比較熟悉的這個可見光的儀器
a camera
一個相機
But the camera is really big
但是相機其實很大
it is about three meters high
它是大概三公尺高
people are there
人在那裡就在這樣
Then there is a big mirror
然後有一個很大的鏡片
lens
鏡頭
Then I take my
然後我就我的這個
this film
這個底片
It's like my detector is here
等於是我偵測器就放在這裡
that looks weird
那這個看起來很怪
I don't know what it is
這不知道是什麼
This is
這是
Gamma Ray is high energy
Gama Ray就是高能量這個
This telescope of electromagnetic waves
電磁波的這個望眼鏡
then why make it like this
那為什麼要做成這樣
He hopes that when these electromagnetic waves come
他是希望這些電磁波來的時候
he used very
他用很
very low angle
很低的角度
call me this
去打到我這個
scattered leaves
一片一片的散葉
Then
然後
let him do this
讓他做這個
This scattering at very low angles
非常低角度的這個散射
Because usually this high-energy electromagnetic wave can easily penetrate
因為通常這個高能量的這個電磁波他很容易穿透
like we shine light
就像我們照S光
When the same time, the S light is direct
的時候一樣S光就直接
penetrate our body and hit the back
穿透我們身體打到後面去
so you only have very high angles
所以你只有非常高角度
This angle of incidence at very low angles
非常低角度的這個入射角
You want to collect his pick number
你是要把收集到他的選號
so he has a
所以他是有一個
so weird
這樣怪怪的
This is our GOT receiver for observing black holes
這個是我們的觀測黑洞的GOT接收機
Because it is an electromagnetic wave, a microwave with a very long wave field
因為它是電磁波 波場很長的微波
So when it arrives, there will usually be a Fee Home in front of it
所以它到接收的時候 通常前面會有一個Fee Home
It's kind of like a horn
就是有點像是號角一樣
There is a natural function that allows electromagnetic waves to converge
有一個天性的作用 讓電磁波能夠匯聚起來
So usually in microwave receivers
所以通常在微波的接收機
You'll see something like
你會看到類似像這樣的東西
just said so much
剛剛講了這麼多
In fact, on every temperature platform
其實在每一個天溫台上面
Regardless of which band the weather station
不管是哪一個波段的天溫台
In fact, they all carry a lot of different instruments
其實它們都搭載很多個不同的儀器
I will give two different examples here
我這邊就舉兩個不同的例子
One is that these two are binoculars that cooperate with our Tianwen team.
一個是這兩個都是跟我們天溫所有合作的望眼鏡
one is japan
一個是日本
I asked Taiwan about this SUVAR binoculars
我一天問台的這個SUVAR的望眼鏡
what about this
那在這個上面呢
I just listed all the instruments it currently has
我就列的它所有目前有的儀器
look wow
你看哇
one two three four five six seven seven
一 二 三 四 五 六 七 七個
then it is an eight meter telescope
那它是一個八公尺的望眼鏡
then this is the real photo
那這個是真正的照片
my real photo
我這真的照片
It is difficult for you to understand why it can hold so many at once
你很難瞭解說為什麼它一下子可以裝那麼多個
that's actually because
那實際上是因為
it has several focal points in this telescope
它在這望眼鏡有好幾個焦點
several that is to say
好幾個這樣就是說
i have a primary mirror
我有一個主鏡
What about the light in space?
那太空的這個光線呢
After reaching my primary mirror
達到我主鏡之後
I can image right where the main focus is
我可以在主焦的地方就成像
I can make a camera right here
我就可以在這邊做一個相機
For example, this wide-angle mirrorable light camera is placed here
比如說這個廣角的可鏡光相機就是放在這裡
Then I have another imaging method
那我有另外的其他的成像方法
That's when I replaced this camera with a lens and another lens
我就是把這個相機把它用鏡片另外鏡片取代的時候呢
Then my signal will go to my this
那我的訊號就會進到我的這個
we are called
我們叫做
cover in green focus , another focus
蓋在格林焦點,另外一個焦點
So it can also put other instruments here
所以這邊它也可以放其他儀器
Usually these two instruments usually have different resolutions
通常這兩個儀器,通常它的解析度會不大一樣
The resolution of the main focus instrument will be better than this
主焦點儀器的解析度會比這個
In this cover forest focus, the one above is slightly worse
在這個蓋森林焦點,上面的這個要稍微差一點
In addition, there are two platforms on both sides of it
另外它兩邊還有兩個平台
How to use two flat platforms
兩個平的平台要怎麼用呢
That is, I put this in the middle of the light input and add another mirror
就是我把這個在光入的中間再加另外一個鏡子
we're going to have a third mirror
我們就要第三次鏡
The third mirror is when my light hits the trail and after my second mirror
第三次鏡就是我光線打到逐徑,打到我次鏡之後
Then hit this third mirror, which can make my light go to both sides
再打到這第三次鏡,可以讓我的光線往兩邊走
what is the advantage of going both ways
兩邊走的好處是什麼
It is on these two platforms
就是這兩個平台上面呢
The instruments on it will not move with the telescope
它上面的儀器是不會隨著這個望眼鏡移動
is suitable for very high-resolution observations
是適合做非常高解析度的觀測
So on a binoculars, you can see that there are many
所以在一個望眼鏡上面,就可以看到有很多
different this instrument
不同的這個儀器
If these instruments are carefully analyzed
那這些儀器如果仔細分析
i use different color words
我用不同的顏色字
put some emphasis on it
把一些重點把它打出來
Look, visible light, visible light, visible light
你看 可見光 可見光 可見光
Infrared ray Golden outer ray Infrared ray Medium yellow outer ray
紅外線 金黃外線 紅外線 中黃外線
Representatives say different instruments
代表說不同的儀器
You are usually related to its wavelength
你其實通常都是跟它的波長有關係
because of the different wavelengths
因為不同的波長
you need to use different
你需要用不同的
Mainly different detectors
主要是不同的偵測器
Also its lens is different
還有它的鏡頭也不一樣
So usually you an instrument
所以通常你一個儀器
It will only be suitable for a fixed wavelength range
它只會適合在固定一個波長範圍
It has no way to cover very large range
它沒有辦法涵蓋非常大的範圍
This is what we basically
這個就是我們基本上
Limitations of our materials
我們的材料的限制
Material limitations of my shots
我的鏡頭的材料的限制
and the material constraints of my detector
還有我的偵測器的材料的限制
In addition, the biggest difference is
另外還有最大的不同就是
many are cameras
很多是相機
Some can be cameras and can also be used as spectrum camps
有些是可以相機也可以當光譜營
Usually if you want to high-resolution spectrum
通常你如果要高解細路的光譜
it can only see
它就只能夠看
It scatters the light of the celestial body very widely
它把天體的光散得非常的分散
let you get more of this
讓你去得到比較多的這個
There is this information about its elements and its speed
有關於它的元素還有它的速度方面的這個資訊
So what about the spectrometer?
所以光譜儀呢
Usually it's different from the camera
通常就會跟相機也是不同的
It is equal to two different things separated
等於是分開來的兩個不同的東西
That's why it can be a camera at the same time
那有些為什麼它可以同時是相機
cannot be spectrum
不可以是光譜
Usually that's when you're doing this revealing design
通常就是你在做這個光露設計的時候
You need to use your brains a little bit
你要動一些小小的腦筋
For example, I am a moving thing
比如說我一個會動的東西
After I plug this thing in
我把這個東西插進去之後
it turns from camera to spectrum
它就會從相機變成光譜
Such a form to achieve this multi-purpose instrument
這樣子的形式來達成這種多用途的天為儀器
Another example is
那另外的例子是
Another word of our cooperation
我們另外一個合作的話
Already called JCNT
已經叫做JCNT
it's a radio
這是一個無線電
the radio binoculars
這無線電的望眼鏡
it has four different astronomical instruments
它有四個不同的天文儀器
on top of the same binoculars
放在同一個望眼鏡上面
it's actually the same
它其實也是一樣
it will have a mirror to fold
它會有鏡子可以折
When mirrors are folded in different directions
鏡子折到不同的方向的時候
my different astronomical instruments
我的不同的天文儀器
can play its role
就可以發揮它的作用
what does it have on it
在這上面它有什麼
it's the same camera planner
它一樣相機 計畫器
I got a weird thing here
我這邊出了一個比較奇怪的東西
extrapolation receiver
叫外插接收機
This thing is actually in Chinese, I was also the day before
這東西其實中文我也是前一天
while doing this translation
在做這個翻譯的時候
I just found out that it's called an external receiver.
我才發現原來叫做外插接收機
English is called Hitrodai
英文叫做Hitrodai
Receiver
Receiver
it's actually a
它實際上它就是一個
Can know the recent
可以知道近來的這個
this phase of light
光線的這個相位
A receiver for the phase of electromagnetic waves
電磁波相位的一個接收機
it usually has a reference
它通常是有一個參考的
Reference electromagnetic waves come in
參考電磁波進來
follow me from space
跟我從太空中
this signal from
傳過來的這個訊號
interfere
做干涉
Usually you have two signal cell waves with the same wavelength
通常你有兩個波長一樣的訊號電池波
when interfering
干涉的時候
If you know the phase of a battery wave
你如果知道某一個電池波的相位
you can know another phase
你就可以知道另外一個相位
So they have something like this
所以他們是有這個樣的功能
Of course on a cordless phone headset
當然在無線電話耳機上面
It also has astronomical instruments like a normal camera
它還有像一般的相機一樣的天文儀器
In this case, it has many wavelengths
這個的話它的波長就非常多
Scoobatux is currently the world's most powerful observation
Scoobatux目前世界上最具有觀測威力的
this radio camera
這無線電的相機
It provides 450 and 850 micron images
它提供的是450跟850微米的影像
450 microns is just short of our visible light
450微米跟我們的可見光就差了
about 1000 times the wavelength
大概是1000倍左右的波長
Our eyes see red light at about 0.6 microns
我們眼睛看到紅色的光大概是0.6微米
So this is about 1000 times worse
所以這個大概就差了1000倍
so their instruments
所以他們的儀器
When designing, it uses the same materials as ordinary visible light
在做設計的時候它使用的材料跟一般的可見光
The materials used will be different
所使用的材料也就會不同
Then there will be a big difference
然後會有很大的差異
So usually when we do training
所以通常我們在做訓練的時候
For example, I specialize in visible light infrared
比如說我是專門做可見光紅外線
It's hard for me to have this technology with those radios at the same time
我就很難同時有那些無線電的這個技術
So in our astronomical institute
所以在我們天文所呢
We basically split into two big groups
我們基本上分成兩個大的group
One is visible light and infrared light
一個就是可見光跟紅外線
Also do this
另外也就是做這個
Development of everything related to black hole radio
跟黑洞相關的無線電的一切的開發
Well, what is the difference between everything in astronomy and science in general?
好 那天文一切跟一般科學一切有什麼不一樣
We know there are actually many different research units in the House of Representatives
我們知道在眾議院其實有很多的不同的研究單位
There are many with 31
有很多有31個所
Then 20 of these 31 firms probably
那這31個所裡面有20個大概
In fact, there are many, many instruments in the tree pear group and the life science group.
樹梨組跟生命科學組裡面其實也有很多很多的儀器
So what is the difference between these instruments and our astronomical instruments?
那這些儀器跟我們天文用的儀器有什麼不一樣
Probably these three points
大概就是這三點
is the first
就是第一個就是
There is no way to control what astronomy observes
天文它所觀測的東西都是沒有辦法控制的
and it's far away
而且是在非常遠的地方
So its signal is quite weak when it reaches the earth
所以它的訊號傳到地球的時候就相當的微弱
there are of course few exceptions
那當然有少數的例外
For example, if I want to look at the sun
比如說我如果要看太陽的話
the sun is actually very, very bright
它太陽其實非常非常亮
Our usual nighttime instrument
我們一般的這個夜間用的儀器
Once placed in the sun, it burns immediately
一放到去看太陽立刻就燒掉
the whole thing is broken
整個就壞掉
So in the field of astronomical instruments
所以在天文做儀器的領域裡面
Being the sun is actually a very special
做太陽其實是一個非常特別的
What they need to consider is also very different from that of ordinary astronomical instruments used at night
他們需要考慮的東西跟一般夜間用的天文儀器也是非常不同
But most astronomical instruments still target this very weak signal
但大部分的天文儀器它還是針對這個非常微弱的訊號
to do
來做
to make this design
來做這個設計
Because this design needs to detect this very small signal
因為這個設計上面要偵測到這個非常微小的訊號
So what it needs is a very quiet environment
所以它需要的是一個很安靜的環境
that's usually in physics because what we think of as a quiet environment
那通常在物理因為我們認為安靜的環境是什麼
Just let the temperature of this thing drop down
就是讓把這個東西的溫度降下去
Especially this detector of yours
尤其是你的這個偵測器
So everyone, do you all have cell phones?
所以大家 大家都有手機嘛
Mobile phones can take pictures
手機都可以拍照
Like the videos of Xiuwa when I first started
像我一開始的時候秀娃那些影片
it's also very beautiful
它也非常的漂亮
These beautiful images have actually been processed.
那這些影像 漂亮影像其實是有被處理過的
It didn't look so pretty in the first place
它並不是一開始就長得這麼漂亮
If that is astronomical, we will lower the operating temperature of the camera to
那天文的話 我們是會把這個相機的工作溫度降到
at least minus 100 degrees
至少是零下100度
What about when you get to minus 100 degrees?
那你到零下100度的時候呢
the pictures you took
你拍照出來的照片
to be very clean
才可以是非常乾淨的
But I'll give some examples later
不過我等一下會舉一些例子
I said it was very clean
我雖然說是非常乾淨
But it's actually relative
可是其實這是相對的
Actually it looks very ugly
其實它看起來是非常的醜
If you haven't dealt with
你如果沒有處理過
but can't stand it
但是看不下去
Another characteristic of silverware after that day is that
那天后银器另外一个就是特点就是
It usually operates around the clock
它通常是全年无休的运转
i put a telescope
我把一个望远镜
Tin Hau silverware placed on top of the mountain
天后银器放在高山上面
What about this mountain?
那这个高山上面呢
we need to
我们需要
There are observation plans every day
每天都有观测的计划
These observation plans are usually decided half a year ago
那这些观测计划通常在半年以前就已经决定了
just if i'm going to go ahead with tonight's plan
就是如果我要进行今天晚上的计划
Actually scientists
其实科学家
Should have been six months ago or earlier
应该在六个月之前或是更早
put forward his observation plan
就把他的观测计划提出来
That came up with some censored work
那提出来有一些审查的工作
So about three months ago
所以大概在三个月之前呢
what to observe every day
所有每一天要观测什么的
This observation plan has been fixed
这个观测计划都已经被固定了
then this i have
那这我已经
so here comes the day
所以到了这一天
if it's my turn i hope this telescope is good
如果轮到我就希望这个望远镜是好的
this silverware is good
这个银器是好的
if it breaks i'm
如果坏掉我就是
I am the opportunity to go public
我就是上市的这个机会
Then I may have to wait another half a year for this
那我可能又要等半年以后才有这个
Opportunity to observe
觀測的機會
So our observed
所以我們對這個觀測的
Stability requirements are very, very high
穩定度要求非常非常高
Which weather station are we usually comparing
通常我們在比較哪一個天溫台
when it works better
運轉比較好的時候
I'm just comparing the light environment
就是在比說這個光環境
It will be broken for a few days a year
到一年壞掉幾天這樣子
That good weather platform may be 365 days a year
那好的天溫台可能一年365天
It's only about 5% broken
它大概只壞掉5%
5% of the days
5%的日子
So about 10 days or so
所以大概就是10天左右
10 days like this
10幾天這樣子
that relative to your instrument
那相對你的儀器
The instrument must be very stable except for the external environment
儀器除了外境要很穩定
The instrument must be very stable
儀器要很穩定
This way you can satisfy these
這樣子你才可以滿足這些
Astronomer Observational Needs
天溫學家觀測的需求
That's another
那另外就是
this temperature environment
這個天溫環境
usually just good weather
通常就是要天氣很好
no cloud place
沒有雲的地方
So it's a relatively dry environment
那所以它是相對乾燥的環境
what about the earth
那在地球呢
This relatively dry environment
這個相對乾燥環境
Usually means that the temperature is very low
通常就是代表是溫度很低
low humidity
溼度也很低
So what about our instrument
所以我們的儀器呢
You have to work in a very low environment
你要在很低的環境下面來工作
So put
所以把
If you put ordinary things in a low-temperature and low-humidity environment,
如果把一般的東西擺到低溫低溼度的環境的時候
sometimes it doesn't work properly
有時候它就不會正常的運轉
The most commonly cited example is the
我們最常提到的例子就是
Usually the sky culture is already a high mountain
通常天文化已經是很高山
So a high mountain means that its air pressure is also very low.
所以高山代表是它的氣壓也很低
The air is relatively thin
空氣也是相對很稀薄
So in the early days, if you took the hard drive to the mountain
所以在早期你如果把硬碟拿到山上的時候
That hard drive often fails
那硬碟常常壞掉
Because the hard disk is actually very fast to read
因為硬碟其實它是很快的去讀取
it spins a fast motor
它會旋轉很快的馬達
It is because of its fast rotation speed
它是靠它的旋轉速度很快
Then float up to do this reading action
然後浮起來去做這個讀取的動作
These drives usually have a high failure rate in the mountains
這些硬碟通常在山上失敗率很高
Motors because the air is too thin
因為空氣太稀薄的馬達
There is no way for others to float it alone
沒有辦法讓人家就獨頭把它浮起來
So there are some very special things in this special environment
所以有一些很特別的在這種特別環境裡面
some very special factors
有些很特別的因素
When you're developing hot weather
當你在進行熱天文氣開發的時候
must be taken into account
必須要考慮進去
ok then i'm back with this photo
好 那我又回來這個照片
Then this photo actually tells you that it is inside an instrument
那這個照片其實就告訴你說在一個儀器裡面
probably something
大概是有什麼東西
the first one is
那第一個就是
We can see that there are of course a lot of screws in here
我們可以看到這裡面當然有很多螺絲
We ignore the screw
那螺絲我們就忽略不計
Did you see it has its lens, has its body
有沒有看到它有它的鏡頭 有它的身體
And then there's this main electronic part of it
然後有它的這個主要的電子零件
And the most important core, the detector inside it
還有它裡面的這個最重要的核心的這個偵測器
Probably just these few
大概就是這幾個就是
Form the core of astronomical instruments
組成天文儀器的核心
you have an optical system
你有一個光學系統
You can go get this signal and put it together
可以去把這個訊號把它匯計起來
after that you have a detector
那之後呢你有一個偵測器
That detector can
那偵測器可以
The data that converts your signal from light to electricity
把你的訊號從光轉成電的資料
there's some circuitry that handles this electron
那有一些處理的這個電子的電路
digitize its signal
把它訊號變成數位化
Then of course you have some mechanical structure
那當然你有一些機設結構
make it reachable
讓它可以穩定的到達
stable automatic development
穩定的自動發展
support your lens
支撐你的這個鏡頭
And this detector of yours
還有你的這個偵測器
then i just said
那我剛剛講了
The first is to speak to the news
第一個就是對新聞訊講說
The most important thing is this astronomical optics system
最重要的就是這個天文光學的系統
that optical system
那光學系統
I just saw it mostly from the camera's point of view
我剛剛大部分都是以相機的角度來看
so you may be
所以你可能就是
that is an imaging system
那就是一個成像系統
That's actually sometimes more than that
那實際上有時候是不只是這樣
because if I want to know its spectrum
因為我如果想要知道它的光譜的話
that's in this optical system
那在這個光學系統裡面
it will have split light
它就會有分光影
Then sometimes there will be this exciter
那有時候會有做這個激化器的這個
this other optical system
這個其他的光學系統
Then I can know the light that comes in
那我可以知道說進來的光
What is the direction of its intensification?
它的激化方向是在什麼樣的方向
The optical system can be said to be in the astronomy department
那光學系統是可以說是天文系裡面
very important part
蠻重要的一個部分
because it actually determines the quality of the image
因為它實際上決定有影像的品質
field of view size and you can achieve this
視野大小還有你可以達到這個
resolution
解析度
The resolution is actually some
解析度其實是有一些
theoretical limit
理論上面的極限
I originally brought another small thing to demo today for everyone to see
我今天本來有帶另外一個小東西要 demo 給大家看
But then it turned out that our laser
但是後來發現我們雷射
not enough
不夠
Not powerful enough for everyone to see
不夠 powerful 可以讓大家看到
but this
不過這個
What is the limit of the so-called optical system?
所謂光學系統的極限呢
Basically everyone if
基本上大家如果
When I was in middle school and high school, I did the limit of diffraction
在國中高中的時候有做過那個繞射的極限
In fact, this is the limit of the diffraction
其實這個就是那個繞射的極限
Diffraction limit means
繞射極限是說
if i had a laser light
我如果有一個雷射光
Then there's a small hole here
然後這邊有個小洞
What about after the laser light passes through the small hole?
那這個雷射光通過小洞之後呢
It will have this circular, this diffracted, this
它會有這個圓圈狀的這個繞射的這個
pattern generated
圖案產生出來
that hole
那這個洞
smaller
越小
The point of this diffraction is larger
這繞射的這個點就越大
what does that mean
那這代表什麼意思
My words, if you take this sock as a
我的話你如果把這個襪子進行當作是
your hole
你這個洞
Then this point represents the one I can image
那這個點代表我可以成像的這個
point size
點的大小
In this way, it can be estimated that
那用這個方法就可以推估說
Where is the limit of this resolution?
這個解析度的極限在哪裡
So when my sea-goggle gets bigger
所以當我的這個望海鏡越大
My image quality
我這個成像品質
That is, the limit of its theory will be smaller
就是它理論的極限就會越小
that wavelength
那波長
It also depends on the wavelength
那它還跟波長有關係
If the wavelength is shorter
波長如果越短
I can also get higher resolution
我也可以得到比較高的解析度
Here I give an example
那這邊我就舉了一個例子
everyone has this phone
大家都有這個手機
In fact, every mobile phone has its lens inside.
其實每個手機裡面它都有它的鏡頭
what about the lens
那鏡頭呢
In fact, it will tell you
其實它都會告訴你說
Your lens has a so called this F Ratio
你的鏡頭有一個所謂的這個F Ratio
So it is F1.8, F2.0
所以它是F1.8、F2.0
or a digital camera that tells you
或是數位相機它有告訴你
How much is this F?
那這個F多少呢
In fact, this is the D
其實就是這個D
in my company
在我這個公司裡面
Large D divides this value of small D
大D除小D的這個值
So you put this value in
所以你把這個值帶進去
then multiply by your wavelength
然後乘上你的波長
you can get your limit
你就可以得到你的極限
So if an iPhone 11 latest
所以如果一個iPhone 11最新的
What about the iPhone 11 Pro?
iPhone 11 Pro的話呢
its resolution
它的解析度
The theoretical resolution limit is
理論的解析度極限就是
about a microphone or so
大概是一個麥克風左右
That's the best that can be achieved theoretically.
那這個是理論上可以達到最好的
this resolution
這個解析度
Actually because you have some
實際上因為你在製作的時候會有一些
optical quality above
光學品質上面
by
受到
when assembling
組裝的時候的
Supply differential impact
供差影響
so this
所以這個
Usually only a theoretical limit
通常只是理論上的極限
Your real imaging will be much better than this
你的真正的成像會比這個還要再
Worse
差一些
I just said
那我剛剛有講過說
our this
我們這個
atmosphere creates labor
大氣會產生勞動
Then this atmosphere produces labor
那這個大氣產生勞動
In fact, it has a great impact on our astronomy.
其實對我們天文上面影響非常的大
Basically if you are
基本上你如果是
when the weather is bad
天氣不好的時候
You can see that this star point keeps shaking
你就看到這個星點一直晃一直晃
so although
所以雖然
When we built this big binoculars
我們蓋很大的這個望眼鏡的時候呢
I theorize it can get very high on this
我理論上它可以得到非常高的這個
resolution
解析度
But the atmosphere is here
可是大氣在這邊
when moving around
動來動去的時候
Actually my resolution
其實我的解析度
will be greatly
就會受到很大的
We just said that Unlimited Power will not be affected by this.
我們剛剛講過無限電是不會受到這個影響
So they came up with a very powerful trick when doing infinite electricity observation.
所以做無限電觀測人他們就想到一個很厲害的一招
is to use special technology to simulate this super large chip
是用特別的技術來模擬這個超大的晶片
What about this huge chip?
那這招超大的晶片呢
The so-called ultra-long limit interference shadow
就是所謂的超長極限干涉影
That is why we can see black holes this time
也就是我們這次為什麼可以看到黑洞
In fact, it uses this antenna scattered all over the earth
其實就是用散佈在地球各地的這個天線
Aggregate this signal of his to simulate a very large chip
把他的這個訊號集合起來來模擬一個超大的晶片
Then I just talked about the limit of this resolution
那我剛剛講過這個解析度的極限
It has something to do with the caliber of my chip.
是跟我這個晶片的口徑有關係
Therefore, if the aperture of my wafer is small
所以我晶片如果口徑很小的時候
My resolution is poor
我的這個解析度就很差
Then I am on the ground, I can best simulate the largest situation
那我在地面呢我能夠最模擬到最大的狀況
It's me who put this antenna in different corners of the world
就是我把這個天線放在世界的不同角落
Then it will have an antenna the size of an earth
那它就會有一個等同於一個地球這麼大的一個天線
Then we can see our black hole
那才可以看到我們的黑洞
You see this and the above tells you
你看到這個 這邊以上都告訴你
When the two antennas are very close, the resolution is not good
兩個天線很近的時候 解析度不好
when i pull it away
我把它拉開的時候
its resolution will increase
它的解析度就會跟著增加
What about the actual operation inside?
那實際上的裡面的這個操作呢
It is more complicated than the concept just now
是比剛剛那個概念還要更複雜
because I'm actually simulating the entire Earth
因為實際上我要模擬這整個地球
When it comes to size, I have several points
大小的時候 我是有好幾個點
That is, my antenna may have seven or eight points
就是我的天線可能有七八的點
in various places around the globe
在地球各地的不同的地方
Then I have to rely on the earth's rotation
那我要靠地球自轉呢
To make up for the distance between this point and the point
去彌補這個點跟點之間的距離
so that my image will become clearer and clearer
這樣我的影像才會越來越清楚
Then this is what we were before
那這個就是我們之前
When doing this black hole observation
做這個黑洞觀測的時候
can get this
可以得到這個
Why can you get such a fresh image
為什麼可以得到這麼清新影像的一個
very important reason
非常關鍵的這個原因
What about visible light?
那在可見光要怎麼辦
is when you have a lot of this old hole
就是當你有很多這個老洞的時候呢
Actually you didn't
其實你又沒有
I can't achieve the effect of the interference I mentioned in the image just now
我沒辦法達到我剛剛這邊這個圖像講的這個干涉的效果
Because the effect of this interference is actually when the signal comes from outer space
因為這個干涉的效果其實是假設說這個訊號從外太空過來的時候
it has not been disturbed by any
它都沒有經過任何的干擾
So what about this light in a different position?
所以這個在不同位置的這個光呢
You can combine it to achieve the effect of imaging
你可以把它合併起來去達到成像的效果
What if you have a large disturbance
那你如果大型的干擾的話呢
My scent information has changed
我的香味的資訊就已經改變了
At this time, I have no way to achieve the effect of this interference.
這個時候我就沒有辦法去達成這個干涉的效果
So in general at the wavelength of visible light
所以一般來說在可見光的波長
We have this phase difference caused by this atmospheric vibration
我們因為有這個大氣搖動造成的這個相差
I have no way to do this intervention
我就沒有辦法做這個干涉的作用
So the interference of the ultra-long line just mentioned
所以剛剛講的那個超長機線的干涉
It's all only possible over the radio.
都只有在無線電裡面才可以達成
in visible light or infrared
在可見光或是紅外線
We're going to use some special methods
我們就要利用一些特別的方法
This has a special term called modulation optics
這個有個特別名詞叫做調製光學
What is the meaning of modulation optics
調製光學的意義是什麼
I want to take this atmospheric old hole out of it
我想要把這個大氣的老洞把它消除掉
Atmospheric old holes usually when light passes through the atmosphere at different altitudes
大氣的老洞通常光線經過這個不同高度的大氣的時候呢
Originally its light should be the red and green lines represent the wavefront of light
本來它的光應該這個紅色跟綠色線代表的是光的波前
That is, when the light signal comes in, you pull up the highest point of its vibration position
也就是光的訊號進來的時候你把它的這個振動的位置的最高點都拉起來以後
Logically it should be flat
照理說它應該是平的
There is this kind of light coming in flat, parallel light coming in
就是有這種平平的進來的光,平行光進來
When the wavefront is this parallel I can get a perfect image
波前是這個平行的時候我就可以得到完美的像
But after passing through the atmosphere, it usually becomes the appearance of the external airflow
但是經過這大氣之中呢其實通常它就變成這個外氣流的樣子
Then if I want to correct the appearance of the external airflow, I have to use a distorted mirror
那我要修正這個外氣流的樣子我就只好用一個可以扭曲的鏡面
I just let this distorted mirror twist along with this my wavefront
我就讓這扭曲的鏡面呢跟著這個我的波前一起扭
Then twist with the wave front
那跟著波前一起扭
It passes through this mirror reflection, and its peeling will be flat
它經過這個鏡面反射,它的剝剪就會平平
After that mediocre, I'll get
那平平的之後,我就會得到
Same as my interference limit
跟我的這個乾涉極限一樣的
such a sharp impact
這麼銳利的影響
that's a video
那這是一個影片
This is King Kate glasses
這個是Kate國王眼鏡
They do this modulation optics
他們做這個調製光學
The image turned out to be blurry
影像原來是模糊的
After I turned on the modulation optics correction
我把這個調製光學的修正打開之後
The image suddenly becomes very sharp
影像突然變得非常的銳利
That's the difference when you take the atmospheric old hole
那這就是當你把大氣的老洞的相差
after fixing it
把它修正完之後
You can get very beautiful images
就可以得到非常漂亮的影像
that beautiful image
那這個漂亮影像
it has some full size restrictions
它是有一些滿大的限制
Because of this atmospheric old hole
因為這個大氣的老洞
different in different positions
在不同位置都長不一樣
we have a noun called
我們有一個名詞叫做
It's your Cohirin's Lens
就是你這個Cohirin的Lens
That is to say, how big is the atmosphere?
就是說大氣在多大的範圍裡面
its old hole is the same length
它的老洞是長一樣的
In Taipei City, this range may only be about 20 centimeters
台北市可能這個範圍大概只有20公分
The environment on the mountain is better
那在山上比較好的環境
maybe a few meters
可能大概是幾公尺這樣子
so you take this
所以你要把這個
When the difference caused by the atmospheric flood is completely corrected
大氣洋洪造成的相差完全修正的時候呢
In fact it is only in this
其實它只有在這個
you can see you can refer to
你能夠看到 你能夠參考
can measure this
可以量到這個
The vicinity of this point where the old cave looks like
老洞的樣子的這個點的附近
will have a good impact
才會得到很好的影響
so you see this
所以你看這個
This frame is actually very, very small
這一個框框其實它非常非常小
It is only 0.8 x 0.8
它只有0.8 x 0.8個
arc seconds
角秒
One arc second is 3600th of a degree
一個角秒是三千六百分之一度
so you know it this is actually watching
所以你知道它這個其實是看
very very small range
非常非常小的範圍
to see this
才可以看到這樣
So usually this
所以通常這個
The problem with modulated optics is that the field of view becomes very, very small
調製光學的問題就是它的視野就會變得非常非常的小
So if it wants
所以它如果要
increase it this
增加它的這個
What about the field of vision?
視野的範圍呢
you just
你就
do some other tricks
做一些其他的技巧
Other tricks include just hitting this laser
其他技巧包括就是打這個雷射
I can shoot lasers in all directions from the wrist glasses
我可以從腕眼鏡上面往四面八方去打雷射
The laser itself is like a reference for me
這個雷射它本身就像是一個我的參考
After the laser hits it, I will look at the point where the laser shines
雷射打上去之後我去看這個雷射發光的點
You can know when you go up and down from this laser
就可以知道從這雷射上去再下來
After this atmospheric god it's old hole look
經過這個大氣神它的老洞的樣子
i can hit several
我可以打好幾個
I'll know after a few hits
打好幾個之後我就可以知道
In this area of ​​the mirror that completes me
在這個完整我的鏡面的這個區域
All Atmospheric Old Hole areas above
上面的所有大氣老洞的區域
This correction actually requires a very fast calculation
這個修正其實是需要很快的計算
because basically you need to achieve
因為基本上你需要達成
More than 500 corrections per second
一秒鐘要修正五百次以上
So you need to have a lot of sensors
所以你需要有很多的sensor
and many lasers
還有很多的雷射
and then go and do it together
然後一起去完成這件事情
This is currently on the Department of Astronomy
這個是目前在天文系上面
It is also a very important field of research
也算是非常重要的一個研究領域
Just to correct the disturbance caused by the atmosphere
就是要去修正大氣造成的困擾
That's another reason
那這個是另外的原因
That's why we have NASA that wants to launch this
就是為什麼我們會有NASA會想要發射這個
Havoc grid average or even the next generation
Havoc網均或是甚至是下一代的
We say that JWST's access to the network
我們說JWST的這個可進網網均
That is, the labor of the atmosphere actually limits a lot of this
就是大氣的勞動其實限制了很多這個
We can reach this limit with ground-based observations
我們在地面觀測上可以達到這個極限
so if you
所以你如果
I just said that the average size of our largest net on the ground is 10 meters
我剛講現在在地面上我們最大網均的尺寸是10公尺
The Havoc net is actually very small, it is only 2 meters
那Havoc網均其實它很小它只有2公尺
Then why can 2 meters see farther than 10 meters?
那為什麼2公尺可以看得比10公尺還要遠
This resolution is an atmospheric effect is a big reason
這個解析度是一個大氣造成的影響是一個很大的原因
Apart from what I just said, that lens is the one
那鏡頭除了剛剛我講的就是那個
What about resolution
解析度之外呢
Of course, its design also has a lot to do with the size of my field of vision.
那當然它的設計也跟我的視野大小很有關係
If my focal length is short
就我焦距如果短
Its field of view is larger
它的視野就比較大
If you have played with the camera
大家如果玩過相機的話
should know
應該都知道
if the shot is short
如果在鏡頭短短的
usually i can see wide
通常就是我可以看得很寬
Then if I have a long lens
那我如果鏡頭長長的
I just zoom in well
我就是放大的效果很好
i can see far
我可以看到很遠
Then of course we're doing astronomical observations.
那當然我們在做天文觀測
We hope that the bigger the field of vision, the better.
我們希望說這個視野能夠越大越好
If the field of vision is larger
那視野越大的話
I will collect this information in a wider range at one time
我一次就會收集比較多範圍的這個訊息
but
但是
When the field of view is bigger
視野越大的時候
The larger the range of angles it enters the light
它入視光的角度範圍越大
so you may have very off-center light coming in
所以你可能會有很偏的光打進來
at this time
那這個時候
when you are doing optical design
你在做光學設計的時候
it will be very very difficult
就會非常非常困難
the other is you
那另外就是你
The last imaged surface
最後成像的這個面
is not a flat
就不是一個平的
so this is a
所以這是一個
the real photo is
真正的照片就是
I discovered a lot of this western alien a while ago
在前一陣子發現了非常多的這個西外星
Because there's this satellite called the Keppel satellite
因為有這個衛星叫做克普爾衛星
that actually
那實際上
This is it
就是這個
It intersects the plane is a curved
它交平面就是一個彎曲的
Because you want to make an imaging system with a large field of view
因為你要做一個很大視野的成像系統
It is difficult for you to adjust the curvature of the field of view itself back
你很難把視野本身的這個曲率把它調整回來
so you end up with
所以你最後就會變成
You have to do your imaging on a curved plane
你必須要在一個彎曲的平面上面去做你的成像
This technology will be much more difficult
這個上面的技術就會困難了很多
This is an example of a visible light camera that we have previously cooperated with Japan
這是一個我們之前跟日本合作的可見光相機的例子
Usually in this lens inside the lens of the whole system camera
通常在這鏡片裡面整個系統相機的鏡頭裡面
There are usually many lenses
通常都有很多片的鏡片
Each lens has its own function
每個鏡片有它不同的功能
It is to correct its chromatic aberration
它可就是修正它的色差
Possibly a fix so that the view doesn't turn into a curved view
可能是修正讓這個視野不要變成一個彎曲的視野
That could be the whole image of this
那可能是把整個影像的這個
twist it to make it small
扭曲把它變得很小
so in one shot
所以在一個鏡頭裡面
Usually very, very many lenses are used
通常會用到非常非常多的鏡片
So this increase in instrument size
所以這個儀器尺寸的增加
These lenses are also getting larger in size
這些鏡片的尺寸也越來越大
You should be able to see it like this
像這個這邊應該可以看到
its 400
它的400
Its radius is 41 cm
它的半徑是41公分
So the whole lens is about 82 cm
所以整個鏡片大概是82公分
That's probably pretty close
這大概是已經算是很接近
The limit of what we can do so far
目前我們可以做到的極限
In addition, if this thing is to be used in infrared
另外如果這個東西是要用在紅外線的時候
Its consideration is different
它的考慮又不一樣
Because this in infrared
因為在紅外線的這個
camera we often need is
相機我們常常需要的是
cooler observed temperature
更低溫的觀測的溫度
I'm going to take all these lenses down to cryogenics
我就要把所有的這些鏡片都降到低溫
How cold is this, probably
這樣要多低溫大概是
around minus 200 degrees
零下200度左右
at minus 200 degrees
在零下200度的時候
you are making this lens
你在做這個鏡片
When it comes to the design of this mirror frame
跟它的這個鏡框的設計的時候
you have to use some special
你就要用一些特別的
Otherwise, we usually say that heat expands and contracts with cold
不然通常我們說這個熱漲冷縮
My lenses shrink slowly
我的鏡片收縮的比較慢
Metals expand when heated and contract when cooled.
金屬它熱漲冷縮的這個幅度比較大
So how do you go about cooling down
那你要怎麼樣能夠在降溫之後
You make this lens able to sustain it
你讓這個鏡片能夠維持它
originally designed location
本來設計的位置
That requires some special design
那就需要一些特別的設計
Let it be a very uniform when shrinking
讓它在收縮的時候是一個很均勻的
There is always something holding it
永遠都有一個東西頂著它
keep it in this fixed position
讓它在這個固定的位置
that in addition
那另外
Design on Infrared
紅外線上面的設計
its lenses are not big
它的鏡片也不大
The composition is also different
組成也結構不大一樣
It is usually divided into two blocks
它通常是分成兩個區塊
One is to let the light coming back from the outer mirror
一個是讓從外鏡回來光
First the paint tool becomes a collimated light at a time
先繪具一次變成一個準直光
that on collimated light
那在準直光上面
We usually have some filters
我們通常會有一些濾鏡
or block the outside mirror
或是阻擋住這個外鏡
The unwanted infrared rays that come in
進來的這個不要的紅外線
Only after that did the second imaging
那之後才做第二次的成像
so it's in the infrared
所以它在紅外線裡面
its lens
它的鏡頭
The number of lenses inside is usually quite a lot.
裡面的這個鏡片的數目通常也是蠻多的
except for this camera
除了這個相機之外
I just said that sometimes what we need is to make it a spectroscopic
我剛剛講過我們有時候需要的是把它做一個分光
This is our participation in another goby project
這是我們參與另外一個光虎魚的計畫的
A pattern for the design of an optical system
一個光學系統的設計的圖案
Usually in this light goby
通常在這個光虎魚裡面
it is very complicated to run
它是跑得非常複雜
In this example it actually has a Xiafeng
在這個例子裡面它其實有一個霞鳳
The light from Xiafeng
霞鳳出來的光
It will hit my zero mirror first
它會先打到我的這個零鏡
and then hit my light
然後之後打到我的光照
And then bounce back after the light
然後光照之後再反彈回來
same same mirror
一樣的同一個這個反射鏡
Let it hit back to the lens of this camera of mine
再讓它打回到我的這個相機的鏡頭
Let this light that has been split
讓這個已經分光的這個光線
can be imaged on my detector
能夠成像在我的偵測器上面
So its optical path is usually three-dimensional and very complicated
所以它的光路通常都是三維的非常複雜
this tossed and tossed
折來折去的這個
In the end you'll end up with a spectrum like this
最後你就會得到像這樣的光譜
This is a high-resolution spectrum
這個是一個高解析度的光譜
You can see this presumably from a microphone
你就可以看到這個大概是從一個麥克風
Up to 2.5 mics the light is all spread out
一直到2.5個麥克風的光全部都散開
Here you will see that I am all this is the one used by our school
這裡面你會看到說我都這是我們校正用的這個
spectral lines so you'll see it's bright all the way through
譜線 所以你會看到從頭到尾它都是亮的
Spectra also come in many different forms
光譜也有很多不同的形式
This is when I only look at one celestial body
這種就是我只看一個天體
Then spread the light as far as possible
然後盡量把它的光散了很開
This is a high-resolution spectrometer
這個是高解析度的光譜儀
There's another one where I want to see a lot of different celestial objects at once
那有另外一種是我一次想要看很多不同的天體
Then make all the celestial bodies line up
那把所有的天體都讓它排列好
Is this fiber optic or
這個是有光纖或是
the shorter one
比較短的這個
Safeng's spectrometer
狹風的光譜儀
Then you see this light of every celestial body
那你就看到每一個天體的這個光
It separates it in a small range
它就讓它分開在一個小小的範圍裡面
So the resolution of this optical auxiliary is relatively poor.
所以這個光輔的解析度就比較差
But I see many celestial signals at once
但我一次就會看到好多天體的訊號
So this topic of different astronomical studies
所以不同的天文研究的這個題目
You need to need different instruments
你就需要去需要不同的儀器
Let you achieve different goals like this
讓你去達成不同的目的這樣子
I just talked about the optical system
剛剛講的是光學系統
Another very important thing is of course the detector
另外一個很重要的當然就是偵測器
After I take the light, whether it is imaging or splitting it,
我把光不管是成像或是把它分光之後
The most important thing is that you have something to convert the signal
最重要的就是你要有東西來把訊號做轉換
The detector will of course determine the sensitivity of the instrument
那偵測器它當然就會決定了這個儀器的靈敏度
if my detector is good
我的偵測器如果很好
Then I can detect very weak signals
那我就可以很微弱的訊號我也可以偵測到
Wait for my temperature to be lower
等我溫度就需要比較低
thank you all
謝謝大家
What about the light? The detector we usually use
那在可精光呢 我們通常常用的這個偵測器
It is the well-known semiconductor
都是大家熟知的這個半導體
Well, there are actually many kinds of semiconductors.
那這隻半導體其實有很多種
Well, what we use most often are thin semiconductors.
那不過我們最常用的就是細的半導體
Then this thin semiconductor is because there are many on the earth
那這細的半導體因為地球上面很多
Then it fits perfectly and fits within our light-detectable range.
那它很剛好的又跟我們這個可精光偵測的範圍
exactly the same
剛好是一致
So what about this fine-made detector?
所以這個細做的這個偵測器呢
That's all the use of this camera
也就管放的使用在所有的這個相機
or in astronomical instruments
或者是天文的儀器裡面
But if you want to detect this wavelength
但是你如果你要偵測的這個波長
If it is longer than the thin detection wavelength
是比細的這個偵測波長還要長的話
Then you can't use this Silicon
那你就沒有辦法用這個Silicon
Then this time you have to use other different materials
那這次你就要採用其他的不同的材料
Materials have their limits
材料都有它的極限
you need to use a different material
你就需要用不同的材料
as detectors for different astronomical instruments
去做不同的天文儀器的偵測器
that's in the detector
那在偵測器裡面
There is a very important factor is
有一個很重要的因素就是
the size of my pixel
我的像素的大小
Because the size of the pixel actually determines your
因為像素的大小其實就是決定你
Final instrument resolution
最後儀器的解析度
no matter i put my light on
不管我把我的光線
How small can it be concentrated
可以集中到多小的範圍
If I am one pixel this big
如果我一個像素這麼大
Then my light is only a little
那我光線只有這麼一點點
I still have the whole pixel lit up
我還是一整個這個像素都亮了
So usually when we design
所以通常我們在做設計的時候
We'll be looking at the pixel size of this detector
我們會在這個偵測器的像素大小
Make a match between my resolution
跟我這個解析度中間來做一個搭配
We usually choose between two and three pixels
我們通常會選擇兩到三個像素
to cover a point of light
來涵蓋一個光點
Theoretically, it is possible to obtain the most effective
理論上是可以得到最有效的這個
most efficient to
最有效的去
We say sample your spot of light
我們說sample你這個光點
a resolution of
的一個解析度
So you can achieve the best resolution with the fewest pixels
所以說你就可以用最少的像素達到最佳的解析度
the opposite
那相反的
That is, if you do it this way
就是你如果是用這個方式去做的話
You can achieve the largest field of view with the least number of pixels
你用最少的像素就可以達到最大的視野
without sacrificing your resolution
而不會去犧牲你的解析度
So something like this
所以大概就是像這個
this pattern below
這個下面這個圖案
What is shown in the image is a
圖像裡面秀的就是一個
For the light of the stars, you have 30 pixels
星星的光大案你有30個pixel
to cover it like this
去涵蓋它這樣子
That's what I just said
那剛剛講過就是
Well
呃
Because we use these for astronomy
因為我們天文用的這些
Binoculars are very large
望眼鏡尺寸非常大
so its this
所以它的這個
long focal length
焦距也很長
When the focal length is very long, the field of view
那焦距很長的時候這個視野
This range covered
涵蓋的這個範圍
Well
呃
with normal mobile phone
跟一般手機裡面
The range that each pixel can cover
這個每一個像素能涵蓋的範圍
There will be a huge difference
也會差距非常大
So the pixels we choose will be different
所以我們在選用的像素的時候會不大一樣
So the pixels of the astronomical visible light camera are about
所以天文可見光相機的像素大概就是
about 10 microns
10個微米左右
that ordinary mobile phone
那一般的手機
A cell phone is about a micron
手機大概是一個微米
then you might want to say
那你可能會想說
a micron
一個微米
i just said
我剛剛講過就是
If a good Apple phone
如果一個很好的Apple的手機
Its lens resolution is approximately
它的鏡頭解析度大概是
The light spot is about a few microns
光點大概是一點幾個微米
So in fact, the P matching of these two
所以其實這兩個的P配
is already very close to what I just said
已經是非常接近我剛剛講的
because you have to think about saying this
因為你要考慮說這個
the lens itself
鏡頭本身
It actually still has some errors
它其實還是會有一些誤差
so it may image quality
所以它可能成像的品質
It's about two to three microns
就大概是兩到三個微米左右
If you use a micron-sized pixel
你如果用一個微米的大小的像素
will reach our
就會達到我們這樣的
Use two to three pixels to cover the point of light
用兩到三個像素來涵蓋光點的
the size of this decision
這種決定的大小
then this is us
那這個是我們
Same as the one that was paired with the lens just now
一樣剛剛那個鏡頭搭配的這個
this detector
這個偵測器
then it this is a
那它這個是一個
900 million pixel astronomical camera
9億畫素的天文相機
Then this 900 million pixels put it together
那這個9億畫素把它拼起來
because a pixel is big
因為一個像素很大
So it's about the size of your arm
所以大概就是你手臂圍起來這麼大的一個範圍
That's like our normal camera
那跟我們一般的相機
Commercial cameras are very different
商用的相機就是有非常大的不同
Commercial cameras we want to say
商用的相機我們希望說
The smaller the better with this thing
有這個東西做得越小越好
The smaller the phone camera, the better.
手機的相機也是越小越好
that astronomy is the opposite
那天文是相反
Tianwen hopes that the bigger the better, the better.
天文是希望這個東西做得越大越好
the bigger words
那越大的話
The better you can have this resolution
你就可以有越好的這個解析度
The camera used for astronomy is usually
那天文用的相機通常
The photosensitive element used in it is also different.
它裡面用的這個感光的這個元件也不大一樣
This astronomy usually we say it uses the structure of CCD
這個天文通常我們說它是用 CCD 的結構
It is CCD and its noise is relatively small
它 CCD 它的產生的雜訊比較小
Then if you want to use our general commercial CMOS Sensor
那你如果要用我們一般商用的這種叫 CMOS Sensor
that looks about the same
那看起來差不多
You can't tell it's any different from the outside
你外觀上面看不出來它有什麼不一樣
Anyway, it's all black.
反正都有一片黑黑的這樣子
that black thing
那這個黑黑的東西
The structure inside is not the same will cause it
裡面的結構不大一樣會造成它
has some disadvantages and some advantages
有一些缺點,有一些優點
Generally speaking, CDs for astronomy
那一般來說,天文用的CD
Its detection rate and sensitivity are very high
它的偵測率,靈敏度很高
There is very little noise, but it reads very slowly
雜訊很小,但它讀的速度很慢
So when I'm taking pictures, I'm just very, very slow
所以我在拍照的時候,我就是非常非常慢
No way, just like this camera can
沒有辦法,像剛剛這個相機可以
It's almost like making a video, it keeps coming
幾乎是像拍影片這樣,一直一直來
keep reading
一直一直讀出來
The one used for general astronomy
那一般天文用的這個
As for this Sensor, you can read a page in about a second.
這個Sensor呢,你大概一秒鐘就可以讀一張
So you'll see this image is
所以你就會看到這個影像是
That's astronomical because often we all have to
那天文因為常常我們都要
It's a long exposure, so it doesn't really matter
很長時間的曝光嘛,所以其實是沒有什麼關係
So for the most part, astronomy is
所以大部分來說,天文是
I love using this CD
很喜歡用這個CD
Because of its, relatively speaking, its Performance is better
因為它的,相對來說它的Performance比較好
That
那
What about this CMOS camera?
這個CMOS相機呢
its advantage is
它的優點是
The speed is fast, it can do very fast orientation, and can also do some special reading
速度快,它可以做很快速的取向,也可以做一些比較特別的讀取
In some projects, like the one we did with a trans-Neptunian eye
在某些計畫,像我們做的一個海王星外眼星的計畫
We just use a CMOS camera to do it, hoping to be able to capture the brightness of the star twenty or twenty times per second
我們就用CMOS相機來做,希望能夠每秒鐘可以兩二十次這個星星的亮度
So this is to really choose one of the above differences
所以這個是在真正去選取上面的一個不同
What about when you do a good job, when an astronomy department does a good job
那你如果做得很好的時候呢,一個天文系做得很好的時候
As far as the whole can play a very high resolution, this is the big one I just showed
就整個可以去發揮非常高的解析度,這是剛剛我秀的那個很大的
This camera with a large CD gain captures images
有一個很大的CD增益的這個相機拍到影像
That is, it can be inserted into the face all the time, and you can magnify it hundreds of times.
就是可以一直入面,一直入面,你可以放大好幾百倍
Not hundreds of times, you can zoom in tens of thousands of times to see very clear celestial images
沒有好幾百,你可放大好幾萬倍都可以看到非常清楚的天體影像
In that video, I just said that there are 900 million pixels
那一張影片裡面,我剛剛講過有九億個畫素
That 900 million pixels covers a lot
那九億畫素就涵蓋非常多
We can have more astronomical data
我們可以多的這個天文的資料
Let you do this related research
讓你來做這個相關的研究
that visible light
那可見光
Because this Silicon is relatively cheap
因為這個Silicon是相對來說比較便宜的關係
So we can do relatively cheap
所以我們可以做相對來說造價比較便宜
we can spell many
我們就可以拼很多個
like we just said
像剛剛我們講
There are more than 100 pieces of this sensor on the entire glue plane
那個整個膠平面上面有超過100片的這個sensor
what about infrared
那紅外線呢
It is basically because of the material
它基本上因為材料的關係
So relatively speaking, the cost is much more expensive
所以相對來說造價就昂貴很多
This is a project we participated in before
這個是我們之前參與的一個計畫
we used four slices
我們用了四片
One is 4 million pixels
一個是400萬畫素
A total of 16 million pixels of this infrared finishing
總共是1600萬畫素的這個紅外線整理
That 16 million pixels seems to say
那1600萬畫素就好像說
Hey, my phone is better than his
欸 我手機都比他好
Eh, yes, there is nothing wrong with that
欸 對 其實是這樣沒有錯
but this one this one
但是這個 這個這個一個
four
四個
four add up to
四個加起來是
Well
呃
I remember correctly, it was 60 million Taiwan dollars
我沒有記錯啊 是六千萬台幣
These are the four
就是這四個
It will be so small when put together
它拼起來就會這樣小小一個
Then why this is because it
然後為什麼這樣是因為它
its making is complicated
它的製作很複雜
it usually takes a
它通常需要一個
there is one
有一個
The detailed circuit for this readout is below
細的這個讀出的電路在下面
Then each pixel
然後每個畫素
Each pixel, it has a little this
每個畫素呢 它都有一個小小的這個
We call Yindian
我們叫陰點
Yin this
陰的這個
bump
凸點
Then this Yin bump is in contact with each of these detectors
那這陰的凸點在跟每一個這個偵測器
There is another article about this chip of the detector
有另外一篇是偵測器的這個晶片
each pixel above
上面的每個像素
to connect it
來把它相連接
Then you can put this
那這樣你才可以把這個
The signal from the detector
偵測器這邊的訊號
Read it out through the circuit of this Srika
透過這斯里卡的電路把它讀出來
that's because of this thing
那因為這個東西
Usually need to work under very low temperature
通常需要在很低溫下面工作
like we did see before
像我們做之前看到
The way this thing works is two hundred degrees below zero
這個東西它工作的路是零下兩百度
So there is a lot of this hot account very wrong
所以有很多的這個熱帳很錯
You don't want it to break in the middle
你又不希望它中間壞掉
So the technology here is quite, quite complicated.
所以這裡面的科技是相當相當的複雜
So that's why it's so expensive
所以造成它為什麼會這麼昂貴的原因
it's expensive though
它雖然昂貴
But in fact, it will show this video after a while
可是其實它等一下會秀這個的影像
you won't believe this
你會不敢相信這個要
one is so expensive
一個要那麼貴
Then what I made seems to be not so good
然後我做出來的東西好像又不是那麼好
Apart from this you have to have a mechanical system
除了這個之外就是你要有機械系統
Just some shutters
就是有些快門啊
Then the cryogenic system
然後低溫系統啊
then vacuum
然後抽真空
Because when you want to lower your Sensor to low temperature
因為你要把你的Sensor降到低溫的時候
If you didn't vacuum
你如果沒有抽真空的話
Then the whole system is completely deiced.
那整個系統全部都解冰
so you need to vacuum
所以你就需要抽真空
then low temperature
然後低溫
then there are some motors inside
然後裡面有一些馬達
If I want to exchange this filter of mine
我如果要交換我的這個濾鏡的話
then i need a motor
那我就需要馬達
and then some are mechanical arms
然後有一些是機械手臂
Then the shutter looks like this
然後快門這樣子
The appearance of these things is actually very important
那這些東西中模作樣其實它也很重要
Because these things have the speed at which they work
因為這些東西有工作的速度
will affect the speed of your observations
會影響到你的觀測的速度
that its accuracy
那它的準確性
will also affect the one you observe
也會影響到你觀測的這個
overall accuracy
整個的準確性
then this is
那這是
One of the first infrared cameras we worked on
我們最早參與的一個紅外線相機
it looks like this
它整個就長這個樣子
there
那裡面
That's the big vacuum gun and the cryogenic system
這就是很大的真空槍跟低溫系統
over here is my cooler
那這邊是我的冷卻機
That cooler is connected to this one
那冷卻機就連到這一個
just open the middle
就是把這中間打開
After opening this
打開以後這個
Then there is green
然後這邊有綠綠的
its filter
它的濾鏡
that big filter ring
那一個很大的濾鏡環
can be rotated here
在這邊可以旋轉
to rotate
旋轉
just go to when you need a different color
就轉到你需要不同顏色的時候
just turn
你就轉
turn that filter ring
轉那個濾鏡環
I just forgot to mention that
那剛剛我忘記提了
astronomical this
天文的這個
image has a
影像有一個
normal camera
跟一般的相機
big difference
很大的不一樣
It's me, in fact, every time I shoot it, it's black and white
就是我其實我每次拍出來都是黑白的
That is, when everyone takes pictures, they will be colored as soon as they are taken.
就是大家拍照的時候一拍就彩色
Then why are you shooting in color?
那為什麼你們拍的是彩色
Because we shot in black and white
因為我們拍的是黑白的
That's because in your
那是因為在你們的這個
There is this green light film in front of the Sensor of the camera
相機的這個Sensor前面有我們說的這個綠光片
Color green film is usually four pixels inside
彩色綠光片通常是四個像素裡面
two are green and one is blue and one is red
有兩個是綠的然後一個是藍的一個是紅色的
Four pixels produce a
四個畫素產生一個
this image in color
有顏色的這個影像
We don't usually do that in astronomy we just take a photo
天文上面我們通常不這樣做我們就是拍一張照片
We put different color filters in front of this real series
我們就在這個真正系列前面放不同的顏色的濾鏡
So I take an image of it could be a green image and then a blue image
所以我拍一張它可能是綠色的影像再來是藍色的影像
Then there is the red image, then I will combine these three images together
再來是紅色的影像那我再把這三個影像合在一起
It becomes a colored image like this
變成是一個彩色的影像這樣子
Then why do you do this like this?
那這樣子為什麼要這樣做主要就是
If I use the general practice of this Sensor
我如果用一般的這個Sensor的做法
I have two greens and one red and one blue and when I put it together I actually have some information
我有兩個綠色然後一個紅色一個藍色那我拼起來的時候其實我有一些資訊
It was private at the meeting because I was equal to two blues with one in the middle
會上私掉因為我等於是兩個藍色中間是一個
There is also a blank space between the two reds
空白兩個紅色中間也是一個空白
Such a resolution will be problematic for real scientific research
這樣的解析度在進行真正的科學研究上面是會有問題的
So astronomy is usually achieved by exchanging filters
所以天文上面通常是用交換濾鏡的方式來達成
The filter exchange system just talked about the rotating disk
濾鏡交換系統剛剛講的是旋轉盤
This is another form we made, like a robot
這個是我們做的另外一種形式是像是機器人一樣
What about this robot?
那這機器人呢
He works differently
他工作的方式就比較不同
This is a place where we put this whole thing
這是一個我們把這整個東西
Fast forward eight times
快轉八倍速
Let's see how he does it. Basically we put
來看看他怎麼做他基本上我們把
our filters
我們的濾鏡
put this
放在這個
I made the inside of the filter holder
我做濾鏡夾裡面
there are three in there
那裡面有三個
There are three on each side and there's one in here
每一邊有三個然後這裡面有一個
Mechanical arm
機械手臂
The robotic arm can
機械手臂可以把
put in my
放在我的
in front of the detector
偵測器前面的
filter take it away
濾鏡把它拿走
after taking it away
拿走之後呢
There will be a raw sauce station and another raw sauce station
這邊會有一個生醬的台 另外一個生醬台
Then this raw sauce station can be used to choose different filters
那這個生醬台可以來選擇不同的濾鏡
That mechanical arm in the back
那後面那個機械手臂
Push my filter in again
再把我的濾鏡推進來
Okay, let's do this filter swap
好 來做這個濾鏡交換
that thing
那這個東西
In fact, it is no different from ordinary mechanical arms.
其實跟一般的機械手臂沒有什麼不一樣
but it's very demanding
但是它要求非常高
the first is
第一個就是
Every time I put the filter back on
我每次濾鏡放回來的時候
The repeatability of the position should be very good
位置的重複性要很好
So our
所以我們這個
every time you put it back
每次放回來的時候
Its error is 10 microns
它的誤差是10個微米
10 microns is
10個微米就是
Of course 1/1 of your hair
當然你頭髮的1分之1
So I can be positioned very accurately
所以我就可以定位得很準
Because the positioning is accurate
因為定位要準
so my image
這樣我的影像
When I want to stack images of three colors together
我要把三個顏色的影像疊在一起的時候
so that there will be no error
才不會有誤差
So it involves a lot of mechanical design
所以這裡面就牽扯到很多機械的設計
how do you get this robot to work
你怎麼樣讓這個機械人在工作的時候
can be very stable
可以很穩定
and then you can put those filters in the same place each time
然後每次就可以把這些濾鏡放在同一地方
That's another
那另外就是
I want this thing to be very stable
我要這個東西非常穩定
So I remember our requirement at that time was
所以我記得我們那時候的要求是
i want this thing
我希望這個東西
RUN a thousand times will not break
RUN一千次都不會壞掉
So when we started, we actually
所以我們一開始的時候其實也
It took a lot of effort to make this system stable
花了很多功夫把這個系統穩定性把它
raise it all the way up to be able to
把它一直提升到能夠
It's been running all the time without any problems
一直一直的運轉都不會出問題
Besides these three things, of course
那除了這三個東西之外當然
The most important thing is the so-called electronic system
最重要還有所謂的電子系統
To make it generate this
要讓它產生這個
real need signal
真正是需要的訊號
It's these real devices it needs some signal
就是這些真正的器它需要一些訊號
to make it work
來讓它運轉
Then you also need these signals
然後你也需要這些訊號
These materials from the real department
把真正系傳來的這些資料
digitize it
把它數位化
Then generate the image you want
然後產生你要的影像
What about after the image is produced?
那產生影像之後呢
That still needs a lot of this software system
那還需要很多的這個軟體系統
to make this system
來做這一系統制
and data processing
還有資料處理
Then I just said that we have
那我剛剛講了我們有
make a big this
做一個這麼大的這個
Before this stitching
這個拼接前
In fact, if you go to see the original filming of it
那實際上你如果去看它原始拍出來
Like actually it's really miserable
像其實它真的是滿慘的
You see this has a lot of things you don't want
你看這個有很多你不想要的東西
For example, white dots, black dots
比如說白點啊 黑點啊
Then everything seems to be uneven
然後就每個東西好像都不是很均勻
Logically speaking, if it is a perfect image
照理說如果是一個完美的影像
When you take a picture, this should be all the same brightness
你一拍的時候這應該就是全部大家亮度都一樣
Because this is the one I use to correct my brightness
因為這是我用來校正我的亮度的一個
an image of
的一個影像
It's a pity that there is usually always a
那很可惜的通常在你的系統裡面總是會有
some without some
有的沒有的一些
For example, bad pixels or your failure
比如說壞點啊或是你失敗的
The production process fails, for example
製作過程裡面失敗比如說
in this place you will see
在這個地方你就看到
there is one
有一個
An Output of this Sensor is missing
這個Sensor的一個Output不見了
So it's all black
所以整個都是黑的這樣子
That's visible light
那這是可見光
The safflower line is even worse
紅花線的就更慘
I just talked about the $20,200,000
我剛剛講那個兩千萬兩百萬兩百美金的
The sound and color of these four direction lines
這個四個方向線的聲色
after it's put together
它拼起來之後
you shoot the sky
你往天空一拍
This is what it shows you
它給你看的是這個樣子
Do you have
有沒有
Eh, there is only one horizontal tone
欸 只有一個橫調的
Then there are things like flowers
然後還有像花的東西這樣子
Then we have to find some way to deal with it
那我們就要想一些辦法來處理
Of course I will be the first to know where this horizontal tune comes from.
那當然第一個我要知道說這個橫調是什麼來的
Hengtune is actually
橫調其實就是
it's in this
它在這個
what we call big people
我們所謂的大顆人
when there is no exposure
就是沒有曝光的時候
because you have a hot relationship with itself
因為你有本身有熱的關係
have a hot and active relationship
有熱老動的關係
So it already has a little signal
所以它本來就有一點點的訊號
then this should be deducted
那這個要把它扣掉
In addition, that means that each Sensor
那另外就是說每一個Sensor
It has several different outputs
它有好幾個不同的輸出
Then the endpoint of this output
那這個輸出的端點
The magnification of its magnification is not the same
它放大的這個倍率不太一樣
So this horizontal dialect
所以這個橫調文
Mainly because the magnification ratio is not the same
主要是因為這個放大的倍率不一樣
what about the other
那另外呢
It's on every Pixel
它每一個Pixel上面
Sometimes because of its Coding relationship
有時候因為它Coding的關係
Its detection efficiency is not the same
它的這個偵測的效率不一樣
So there will be some very strange patterns
所以會一些很奇怪的這個Pattern
We can all find a way to get rid of this Penet
這個Penet我們都可以想辦法把它去掉
Then remove the bad points
然後再把壞點去掉
Especially this side and here are all bad
尤其是這個旁邊這邊全部都是壞的
then remove it like this
那就把它去掉這樣子
Then you can get the corrected image
那你就可以得到校正以後的影像
Then the corrected image is not the final one yet.
那這校正以後的影像還不是最後的
Because in the infrared this sky background
因為在紅外線這個天空的背景
it has been changing over time
它一直隨著時間改變
so you're going to get another no
所以你要得到另外一個沒有
This background without celestial bodies
沒有天體的這個背景
Finally you can actually get one of these
最後你才可以真正得到一個這個
finally finished
最後完成
then you will see this inside this
那你就會看到這個裡面這個
We say we are very lucky
我們說很幸運很區域
will show up clearly
就會很明顯的呈現出來
So this image processing in astronomy is
所以這個影像處理在天文裡面是
very very important
非常非常重要
Without image processing
沒有影像處理的話
You'll never see such a beautiful image
你永遠看不到這種這麼漂亮的影像
Actually it is
其實就是
It turned out to be super scary
原來拍出來都是超級恐怖
no way
沒有辦法
you can't believe this
你沒有辦法相信這種
Of course, the black hole just mentioned is also
那當然剛剛提到這個黑洞也是
I think if you guys have listened to our previous speeches or press conferences,
我想如果大家有聽過我們之前的這些演講或是記者會的話
We only need to do this ultra-long limit interference and data processing
我們單單要做這個超長極限的干涉以及的資料處理
There are four teams in different parts of the world
就有四個team在世界不同的地方
Then it took a year to process
然後花了一年時間來處理
That's all data processing
那這個都是資料處理
actually very very important
其實是非常非常重要的
What you just said is usually on the ground.
那剛剛大家講的通常都是在地面上的
What problems will we encounter when developing on the ground
我們在地面上做開發的時候會遇到什麼問題
Finally, take a moment to talk about this space abandoned development
那最後花一點時間來講這個太空遺棄開發
That is different from the ground, in fact, it means
那跟地面不一樣其實就是說
My abandonment has to be able to withstand the launch process
我的遺棄必須要能夠承受發射過程
There is usually a lot of vibration during the launch.
那發射過程裡面通常都是有很大的震動
and then a lot of this noise
然後很多的這個噪音
Of course it can still operate in the space environment
那當然它還能夠在太空的環境下面運轉
that besides this
那除了這個之外
Say goodbye to me when you fly up
飛上去之後就跟我說再見
Then if I fly up and break
那我如果飛上去之後壞掉
I really have no way
我就真的是完全沒有辦法
Like Harvard, it is possible to send space theory to repair it. The probability is
像哈佛一樣可以派太空說上去修的這個機率是
Only about two times
絕無僅有大概只有這兩次
Now there is no space to say that you can fly to this space.
現在也沒有太空說可以飛到這個太空了
So he has high requirements in his heart
所以他都有內心的要求很高
So mostly he uses proven techniques
所以大部分他使用的都是已經驗證過的技術
That is, no one will use unverified
就是沒有人會用沒有驗證過的
so we say
所以我們說
we usually joke
我們通常都開玩笑說
In fact, all the satellites use technologies ten years ago.
其實這個所有衛星上面用的都是十年前的技術
Because you want the technology from ten years ago
因為你要十年前的技術
then mature
然後成熟之後
Then after a long time to do verification
然後經過很長的時間來做驗證
Because space one has a lot of extra testing
因為太空一期有很多額外的測試
You're going to do a radiation test
你要做抗輻射測試
There is a lot of radiation in space
太空中有很多的輻射
This evidence test
這個證供測試
You have to be able to work in the space environment
你要能夠在太空這個環境工作
The space environment is very special, that is, your satellite is usually rotating
太空環境很特別就是通常你這個衛星在轉
Where the sun shines is hot
我太陽照到的地方很熱
it's cold when turned to the back
轉到背面的時候很冷
so they need to do some
所以他們需要做一些
Fractuation at a very special temperature
很特別的溫度的Fractuation
What I just talked about is vibration and noise.
那剛才有講過的就是振動跟噪音
The radiation dose in space
那太空中的輻射劑量
Usually it is 100KR
通常它是100KR
that's a
那這是一個
Anyway, this is a unit of radiation dose.
反正這是一個就是輻射劑量的單位就對了
that's usually in astronomy
那通常在天文裡面
Sometimes you have very special situations
有時候你會遇到很特別的情況
That is, you are going to launch this satellite to a farther place
就是你要把這個衛星發射到更遠的地方
For example, the harshest place is Jupiter
比如說最嚴苛的地方就是木星
So everything has to be tested first
那所以所有東西都要先測過
that's our detector
那這是我們的偵測器
I don't know if you can see clearly
我不知道各位看得清楚
Are these two different?
這兩個有不一樣嗎
No
沒有
Sorry about the resolution problem
不好意思 解析度的問題
In fact, it is our device to fight
實際上就是我們這顆器去打
This radiation dose after doing this test on the ground
這個輻射劑量在地面上做這個測試之後
it will have a lot of white spots
它會有很多的白點
But here, sorry to see it out
不過在這邊,不好意思看把它出來
Then Jupiter, if you go to Jupiter, play Jupiter is the earth
那木星,你如果要去木星,玩木星是地球
all this
所有的這個
The magnetic field inside the form is the largest
形式裡面的磁場最大了
The magnetic field is the largest, and its magnetic field lines
那磁場最大,它的這個磁力線
will capture more of this generation of electric particles
就會捕捉更多的這個代電力粒子
So the radiation it catches will be even greater
那所以它捉招的輻射就會更大
so before
所以之前
Then it is the satellite of Safari, Geno
那它Safari這個Geno的這個衛星
it
它
You see it's the dose
你看它是劑量就是地
250 times around the lower satellite
繞低衛星的250倍
So you're testing higher doses like this
所以你測試的劑量就要更高這樣子
so it is
所以它是
a satellite it protects
一個衛星它的保護
In order to protect the instrument inside it from letting the
為了保護這個它裡面的儀器不讓這個
radiation killed it
輻射把它打死
it retakes 100
它就重拿100
80 kg like this
80公斤這樣子
so it
所以它
This satellite actually shrinks the outer layer of its instruments
這個衛星其實它的縮了儀器的外層
It is packed with a lot of this very thick this
都是包了一大堆這個非常厚的這個
stereotype
鉛板
let it not be this
讓它不會被這個
The radiation in this space killed it
這個太空裡面的輻射把它打死
But this is what I just said
但是這個是我剛剛講的
We usually in the satellite development process
我們通常在衛星的開發過程
We need a lot of this semo cycle
我們就需要很多這個semo cycle
I put this thing
我把這個東西
The whole instrument cools it down
整個儀器把它降溫
depends on the orbit of your satellite
就看你衛星的軌道
Usually if it is in an orbit relatively close to the earth
通常如果是離地球比較近的軌道
probably will be in
就大概是會在
Temperature between plus 50 degrees and minus 50 degrees
正50度到負50度之間的溫度
just let it do the loop
就讓它做循環
Of course because in space it is
那當然因為在太空中是
It's a complete vacuum so you vacuum up the whole instrument
完全是真空的狀態所以你整個儀器就把它抽真空
then heat it inside
然後在裡面加熱
or cooling heating cooling
或冷卻加熱冷卻
then keep watching
然後一直看
see if there is any problem with it
看它有沒有什麼問題
Then there is the so-called vibration
那另外就是所謂的震動
This is the instrument we made before
這是我們的之前做的儀器
failure example
失敗的例子
Actually it's this
其實它這個
We put the instrument on a vibrating table
我們把儀器裝到一個這個震動的台子上面
Then it will simulate the vibration when launching
然後就會模擬發射的時候的震動
After finishing, my board fell off
整完之後我的板子就掉下來了
because when we design
因為我們設計的時候
it's in the process of processing
它在加工的過程
It's just the design
就是設計沒有問題
But when processing
但是在加工的時候
it will generate some
它會產生一些
I said that the hard power is on this board
一些我說硬力在這個板子上面
so it breaks when you shake too much
所以你震動太大的時候它就會斷裂
So these vibrating
所以這些震動的
all design matters
所有的設計都有意義
Letting you equal to making your design better
讓你等於是讓你的設計更好
so that it can really stand up to your design
讓它可以真正承受你的設計上面
launch all questions
發射所有問題
So there will be no problem when actually launching
所以真正發射的時候就不會有問題
It can be launched smoothly
它就可以很順利的發射上去
in this way
這樣子
It's actually pretty cool to watch this launch.
看這個發射其實還滿酷的
is how much it shocks you
就是它給你的震撼的程度
thank you all
謝謝大家
elliptical orbit satellite
橢圓軌道衛星
The place where the lowest ball is the lightest is about 300 kilometers
最低球最輕的地方是大概是300公里
The farthest place is about 10,000 kilometers
最遠的地方大概是接近1萬公里左右
It's all about what we're going to do
剛剛講的都是我們要做什麼
then what's the point of these things
然後這些東西有什麼重點
what is his challenge
那他的挑戰是什麼
we just said you do one thing
我們剛剛講說你做一件事情
I often want to say that angels, righteous people and
常常都想說要天使地義人和
If you ask me, is there any abandoned development now?
如果你問我說現在遺棄開發有沒有
In fact, I told you everything is not
其實我都跟你講全部都沒有
we are doing this
我們在做這個
Abandoned development is always true
遺棄開發老說真的是
It's really a very, very difficult situation right now.
現在真的是遇到非常非常困難的一個境界
The first is the astronomical
第一個就是天文去期
I want to say that after the big problem
我想講這問題很大之後
it's all big
這一切很大
It's all big and he's been developing it for a long time
那一切很大他開發的時間很長
So now we often joke that
所以我們現在常常開玩笑說
you make a plan now
你現在做一個計畫
When will you finish this project?
那你做這個計畫什麼時候結束
He can finish it when I retire
等我退休的時候他才可以完成
So you often have a problem
所以你常常遇到一個問題
It means you do this for a long time
就是說你做這個很長的
when planning for a long time
時間很長的計畫的時候
How do you attract people to invest
你要怎麼樣吸引人來投入
Actually this is a big problem
其實這是一個很大的問題
Of course the bigger you do this thing
當然你做這東西越大
The more money you have
你的經費也越多
So cross-border cooperation is normal
所以跨國合作是很正常的
We are often several countries
我們常常都是好幾個國家
come and do this together
來一起來做這個事情
This is another project we have in Mexico
這個是我們另外一個在墨西哥的計畫
We're going to this observatory in Mexico
我們要在墨西哥的這個天文台
The Science of Building Three Telescopes to Make This Eye Star
蓋三個望眼鏡做這個眼星的科學
then you will see this snow
那你會看到這個有雪
And then the snow melts and then the snow comes again
然後雪又融了 然後雪又來了
So this plan actually cost
所以這個計畫其實也是花了
close to our ten years
接近我們十年的時間
and then it might be about time to start
然後可能快要可以開始進行
Our observation work
我們這個觀測的工作
Ten years in astronomy is pretty normal now
十年在天文上面現在是一個還蠻正常的
A number is from starting a project to
一個數字就是從開始一個計畫到
it can actually start observing
它能夠真正開始觀測
It's not the end of the project but the start of doing what you want to do
並不是計畫結束而是開始做你想要做的事情
That's like ten years
就是十年這樣子
i just said
我剛剛講過就是
Such multinational projects are also very common
這種跨國的計畫也是很常見
this is mine
這是我的
Another sentence that goes on now
現在進行的另外一句話
You can see how many points there are
你可以看到這有多少個點
A point represents a cooperative unit
一個點就代表一個合作的單位
so you have
所以你有
Five or six different countries at the same time
同時有五六個不同的國家
come
來的
astronomers come together
天文學家一起來
work on this development
參與這個開發的工作
The biggest problem with this forecast is what to do when I have a meeting
這個預料最大問題就是我要開會的時候要怎麼辦
So usually you are not very early
所以通常你不是很早的時候
It's late for a meeting
就要開會就是很晚的時候
to do this conference call
要做這個電話會議
this is
這個是
Then by the way why the earth is not flat
那順便說為什麼地球不是平的
why the earth is round
地球為什麼是圓的
That said
那講到
Speaking of
講到
I just talked about the angel Nadili
剛講的是天使那地利
Observatories are usually in that kind of shitty place
天文台通常都在那種很糟的地方
I just talked about a series of design to consider these issues
我剛剛講過一系列設計要考慮這些問題
that work too
那工作也是
This is us in Hawaii, Makia
這個是我們在夏威夷、Makia
We have several observatories here
我們所裡面有好幾個天文台在這裡
I took this photo because our working environment is like this
我拍這個照片是我們工作環境就是這樣
Temperature 1.8C
溫度1.8C
Relative humidity 14%
相對濕度14%
The most important thing is this is
最重要是這個是
This is the air pressure is 620%
這是氣壓是620%
Then we know that the normal ground should be 1000
那我們知道一般正常地面應該是1000
is about half
就是大概是一半左右
So the oxygen in your airway over there is
所以你在那邊呼吸道的氧氣就是
only half of the ground
只有地面上一半
so usually a
所以通常都是一個
In Gaoshan town and very uncomfortable environment
處於高山鎮然後非常不適的環境
I would have liked to put a photo
我本來想要放一張照片
After my colleague got to the top, he quickly brought some oxygen up
我的同事到了上面之後就趕快把氧氣稍帶上去
where to visit
探望在哪裡
then there is
那還有
So on this, if you have to do some very heavy work, it is actually very hard
所以在這個上面你如果要做一些很粗重的工作其實很辛苦
This is when I arrived very early
這個是我很早期的時候剛到
At that time, I was photographed doing this
那時候被拍到下位在做這個
We need to re-enforce this mirror
我們要重度這個鏡面
Therefore, the aluminum of this degree on the entire surface of the mirror should be removed.
所以要把鏡面整個上面的這個度的鋁把它弄掉
wipe it clean
把它擦乾淨
it's very very tiring
這是非常非常累
you have to take this
你要帶著這個
This is the last step
這個已經最後一步
So take that gas mask off
所以已經把那個防毒面具拿下來
you have no oxygen
你已經沒有氧氣
Then you have to wear a gas mask while working
然後你要帶一個防毒面具的時候在工作
it's very very hard
這是非常非常辛苦
Of course, our colleagues in Grinda are also protected from the cold
那當然這個我們在格林達的同事也是保受這個寒冷的襲擊
rarely do you see this
很少你會看到這個
Why did he take this photo because he found this
為什麼會拍這張照片是因為他發現這個
The temperature of color consciousness is almost the same as Huashi
色識跟華式的溫度幾乎是一樣
Then I knew it was Chinese style and it was about 30 degrees
然後知道是華式要30幾度
It's when it's minus 30 degrees
負30幾度的時候才是
When working outside, you have to be fully dressed and there will be no place to show
在外面工作要全副裝也不會有任何一個地方露出來
That person is also the same, our salaries in the war rescue unit are very low
那人和也是,我們在戰營救單位的薪水很低哦
What we need is, of course, what we need are very experienced engineers
那我們需要的是,當然我們需要的是非常有經驗的工程師
It is very difficult for an experienced engineer, and it is difficult for you to attract him with a salary
那這個有經驗的工程師很難,你很難用薪水的方式把它吸引過來
So we usually use, I don't know, we say them, they're cute
所以我們通常都是用,我不知道,我們說他們,他們很可愛啊
They just think it's more fun to work here.
他們就是覺得這裡的工作比較有趣這樣
Or if they are very interested in me, then they will be willing to join our team
或是對一聽我很有興趣,那他們就願意,願意來參與我們團隊
Then of course we often meet people after they come
那我們當然也常常遇到人來了之後
After a year or two of what he learned, he left
來了一兩年他學的東西之後他就走了
So this is a big problem
所以這個是蠻大的問題
He's not just them, even our researcher level is the same
他不只是他們連我們這個做研究員等級也是一樣
Because I have worn one piece every ten years, and I have a piece of paper when I have worn one piece
因為我十年摩一件,摩一件我就是有一片Paper的時候
Because of the normal conditions inside, just kick him out
因為裡面正常的狀況,只要把他踢走了
This director may be clearer
這處長可能比較清楚
It is the cooperation of the researchers of the Central Academy of Sciences
就是中央院隊研究員這個配合
There are actually some requirements for the number of papers
Paper的數目其實是有一些要求的
So how are you putting yourself into this kind of work?
那如何你在投入在這種工作裡面
It can also maintain the output of your paper
還可以維持你的這個Paper的產出
In fact, it is also a very important question
其實也是一個很重要的問題
But I think I've told you so much today
不過我想今天跟大家講了這麼多
I think we've spent the past few years
我想我們在過去幾年
We really did a lot of planning
我們真的是做了非常多的計畫
Cover different this painting glasses
涵蓋不同的這個畫眼鏡
Let these systems be installed on the painting glasses
讓這些系統能夠裝在畫眼鏡上面
and then be able to play their role
然後能夠發揮他們的作用
It is important to hope that they can make
那很重要就是希望他們能夠讓
Astronomers in Taiwan can use these
台灣的天文學家可以使用這些
The instruments we made
我們做出來的儀器
Then do the most cutting-edge astronomical research like this
然後去做最尖端的這個天文的研究這樣子
then we just started
那我們接下來剛剛一開始
the beast talked about
畜生有談到
We are now at least two major projects that I am working on
我們現在至少我自己在負責的兩個重要的計畫
one is
一個就是
Speaker's astronomy satellite
Speaker的這個天文衛星
This is an infrared astronomy satellite
這是一個紅外線的天文衛星
It is a big project of cooperation between Europe and Japan
它是歐洲跟日本合作一個很大的計畫
To send a 2.5-meter astronomical satellite into space
要把一個2.5公尺的天文衛星送到太空
It operates at a lower temperature
它的工作溫度更低
Its entire system is 8K
它整個系統是8K
8K is minus -265 degrees
8K是零下-265度
Almost the brightest mirror connection you can achieve
幾乎是你可以達到最亮的鏡接
We have already begun to design some instruments in this part
我們現在已經開始在做這個部分的一些儀器的設計
This is tantamount to our first project to compare large and astronomical satellites
這個等於是我們第一個比較大型和天文衛星的計畫
So what we're doing now isn't...
所以我們現在做的東西並不...
Participation is not too big
參與的部分並不算太大
But it can provide us scientists to participate in perhaps this first-hand
但是它可以提供我們科學家參與或許這個第一手
Infrared Observation Data
紅外線觀測的資料
The other big project is
那另外一個大的計畫就是
I just talked about the biggest future...
剛剛講過未來最大的這個...
But the golden king has already reached this EOT in Europe
可金汪化已經歐洲的這個EOT
One and the instrument in which we are involved
我們參與其中的一個和儀器
Then this series
那這一系
I just got back from Holland last week to talk to them
我上禮拜才剛從荷蘭回來跟他們談
what parts are we responsible for
我們要負責哪一些部分
Taiwan has done very well because of the processing of some machinery
台灣因為在一些機械上面的加工做得非常好
So we might be responsible for the entire
所以我們可能會負責整個
core part of a series
一系的核心的部分
How big is this series?
那這一系多大
The entire height of this series is approximately
這一系整個高度大概是
2.5 meters
2.5公尺
This width is
這個寬度是
About 1.5 meters
大概1.5公尺
It is easy to put this
很容易就可以把這個
cover it all
整個把它蓋滿
So this is our current
所以這個就是我們目前
Next
接下來的
key work items
重點的工作的項目
so today i
那所以我今天
It is very simple to introduce to you our Tianwen
就是很簡單跟大家介紹的這個我們天文
instruments of these
儀器的這些
and some
和一些
details then
細節然後
some key points
一些重點
The conclusion is that we really need a lot of different talents
結論就是其實我們真的是需要很多不同的人才
Of course, at the same time, our technology does not mean that we can do it ourselves.
當然同時我們這些技術也不是說我們自己做就好
In fact, there are also cooperation with many domestic manufacturers
其實也有跟國內很多的廠商合作
We also undertake some cases of manufacturers to help them do some system development
我們也有承接一些廠商的案子幫他們做一些系統的開發
The hope is that in addition to building our own technology
希望就是除了建立我們自己的技術
It can also help some domestic industries like this
也可以幫助一些國內的產業這樣子
Our astronomical institute was actually able to participate in these important international projects in the past
我們天文所其實在過去能夠參與這些重要國際計畫
In fact, it has a very important correlation with our technological crisis.
跟我們這些技術危機其實是有非常重要的相關性
That's the end of my speech today. Thank you.
那我今天的演講就到這個地方 謝謝
Thank you, Mr. Wang, for your wonderful speech.
謝謝王老師很精彩的演講
At that time, I heard that there are actually people stationed in Hawaii in our courtyard.
我那個時候聽到說我們院裡頭居然還有派駐到夏威夷
At that time, my small mind was probably in YTB
我那個時候心裡頭小的是大概是在YTB
Wow, that's too much, I want to say that life is ashamed, couples play together
哇 那太 我想說人生自恥 夫婦合球啊
Is it okay? Later I found out that they were in Monaca.
可不可以 後來我才知道原來他們是在摩納卡
Mona seems to be that Hawaii
摩納好像就是那個夏威夷
That Monaca seems to be
那個摩納卡啊 好像就是
In fact, Mona actually means three in Hawaii.
其實摩納其實是夏威夷的三的意思
So in the original there is still in Lulan
所以在 原來還有在綠蘭
I heard that wow it looks like a lot in Greenland
我聽到說哇 在格林蘭看起來是很
great place still up
很棒的地方 還要起來
The colleagues at the astronomical institute really worked hard
那個天文所的同仁真的都很辛苦
Then everyone knows that in the Chinese Academy
然後大家知道在中文院裡頭
Let's just say that the research pressure is unbelievable again.
我們可以說研究壓力又大得不得了
So that one said it would take ten years to build an observatory
所以那個說建一個天文台要十年
Everyone knows that we are researchers
大家知道我們做研究人員的
About five or six years will be renewed
大概五年六年就要被續聘
Then if your academic research
然後如果你的學術研究
There is no way to publish a good paper
沒有辦法發表出來好的論文
soon you probably will
馬上大概你一下就會
So this research is incredibly stressful.
所以這研究壓力大得不得了
no matter what
不管了 不說了
thank you all
謝謝大家
What about us today, we have prepared some small gifts
那我們今天呢 我們有準備一些的小禮品
That is whether the presence is aimed at everyone
那就是在場有沒有針對於大家
Teacher Wang's wonderful speech
王老師的精彩的演講
do you have any questions
有沒有什麼任何的提問
Then if you report your name first
那如果您就先報一下您的大名
Then there is your question, thank you
然後還有您的問題 謝謝
After all Huang Qifang I am Datong
畢竟黃 黃啟芳 我是大同
I just learned that our
我剛才了解到說我們的
Sensor for astronomical images
天文的影像的Sensor
The resolution is actually 10 times lower than that of a mobile phone
解析度實際上是比手機低了10倍
10 micro meters and one micro meter
10個micro meter跟一個micro meter
Its pixel size is right
它的像素大小 對
Then such a large optical lens is 10 meters
那麼這麼大的光學的透鏡10公尺
20 meters 30 meters
20公尺 30公尺
so much information
資訊量這麼多
It seems a bit wasteful to use such a thick Sensor
用這麼粗的Sensor好像有點浪費
Then I was wondering if there is a possibility
那我在想說有沒有一種可能
I'm a professor in the Department of Electrical Engineering
我是電機系的教授
Sensor of current commercial camera
現在的商業的相機的Sensor
Tens of millions of pixels
動不動就幾千萬個像素
Maybe its environmental quality
那或許它的環境品質
Cannot meet the needs of astronomy
不能符合天文的需求
Is it possible to use these small Sensors in the future?
那有沒有可能未來再用這些小Sensor
so high resolution
解析度這麼高
Multiply it into an Array
把它多成一個Array
Because I just heard that there is a combination of Sensors
因為剛才聽到有一個Sensor組合起來
just a few hundred million
就是幾億個
Then it may be tens of millions if you use this one like Sony.
那用這個像Sony的可能是幾千萬啊
Tens of millions in a small street
一個小街頭幾千萬啊
That pocket may be worth billions or tens of billions
那兜一大片可能是好幾十億好幾百億
Is it possible
有沒有這個可能
I may not have said a word just now
我剛剛可能沒有講一句
That's why we choose 10 microns
就是我們為什麼要選10個micron
When our pixel size
當我們的像素的大小
actually because
其實是因為
It's because of the big old hole I just mentioned
就是因為我剛剛講的那個大氣的老洞
That’s my optical theory. I can make this optical machine very small.
就是我光學理論上我是可以把這個光機的非常小
Put the dot machine very small
把光點機的非常小
But because of this atmospheric old hole relationship
但是因為這個大氣老洞關係
So my dots get bigger
所以我的光點就變大
Then I don't use a small sensor when the light spot becomes bigger
那我光點變大的時候我就不要用小的sensor
that pitch
那個pitch
to cover it because
去涵蓋它因為
Each pixel will have a noise when read out
每一個pixel在讀出的時候都會有一個noise
so
所以
We will choose the size of this sensor which is about 10 microns
我們才會選大概是10個micron左右的這個sensor的大小
Of course I just said that if you use that
那當然我剛剛有講過說如果用那個
that
那個
modulated optics i can get this quality right
調製光學我可以把這個品質弄得很好
At that time we usually
那那個時候我們通常是
use
用
different way
不同的方式
to lengthen the focal length of my optics
去把我的光學的焦距變長
let it Play Scale
讓它的Play Scale
is the field of view per unit length
就是單位長度的視野
let it change
讓它改變
Of course in astronomy
那當然天文裡面
why do i seem to say
為什麼我會好像說
Like I'm talking about 10 micro
好像我講說10個micro
This pixel doesn't seem to change
這個pixel好像都不會變
The main reason is that
主要原因就是說
In developing these astronomy-specific
在開發這些天文專用的
There are very few companies with this sensor
這個sensor的公司非常的少
This is what we use on our phone
我們手機用的這個
This sensor is related to our own
這個sensor跟我們自己
The sensor we use for astronomy
我們天文用的sensor
The biggest difference is
最大不同就是
Sensitivity of the mobile phone
手機的感光度
The functionality of the sensor is only about 50%
sensor的功能度大概只有50%
good about one percent
好的大概是百分之
Usually about 20 to 30 percent
通常大概百分之二十到三十
More than 90% of the astronomy was used that day
那天文用的都是百分之九十以上
Then this is related to it, the structure is not the same
那這個是牽涉到它這個架構不大一樣
that is
就是
Slowly, the current sensor of the mobile phone
慢慢的手機現在的sensor
also gradually changed to
也慢慢有改成
what we call preparation
我們所謂的備造式
It's light coming in from the back
就是光從背面進去
Because there are many circuits on the Sensor
因為Sensor上面有很多的電路
These circuits will
這些電路會
because it blocks the light
因為它會擋住光
So you can't increase its sensitivity
所以你就沒有辦法提升它這個感光度
Then when you go in from the back
那你從背面進去的時候
it can increase a lot
它就可以增加很多
But this back cover
但這個背罩式的這個
Sensor is
Sensor是
At least CMOS is the Sensor of all our mobile phones
至少CMOS就是我們所有手機的這個Sensor
It has only gradually become popular in the past two years
是這一兩年才慢慢普及
I just mentioned
那我剛好提過
We have a big camera with this CMOS
我們有用一個很大的這個CMOS的相機
That Sensor was actually at the beginning
那那個Sensor其實一開始的時候
We all ask TSMC or UMC to ask them to do
我們都請台積電或是聯電問他們要做
say no
說不要
because they asked
因為他們就問說
large market
市場多大
I said maybe 100 pills a year
我說一年可能一百片吧
then he said goodbye
然後他說再見
So these requirements of astronomy
所以所以天文的這些需求
How can I follow
要怎麼樣能夠跟
with average
跟一般
We still follow the general needs of the industry
我們還是跟產業一般的需求
there is a big difference
有很大的不同
That's unless the two of them can get close
那除非就是他們兩個能夠接近
We have the means to convince these companies
我們才有辦法去說服這些公司
they can invest
他們能夠去投入
in this way
這樣子
Otherwise, it would still be very expensive for us to do
那不然的話我們做還是很貴
one
一位
My surname is Huang
我姓黃
just be
就是就是
just like i see that
就是好像我看那個
It is when the live broadcast is when the black hole is live broadcast
就是直播的時候就黑洞直播的時候
It seems that you will practice that kind of self-discipline
好像你們就會有練那種各各就是
The kind of manufacturers you mentioned just now, cooperation, etc.
剛剛講的那種廠商啊合作什麼之類的
then i see
那我看到
I see Zhonggang, Zhonglong
我看到有中綱啊中龍啊
Then everyone kept writing
然後大家一直寫啦
Then it seems that in this so-called
然後好像就是在這種所謂的
The cooperation between the instrument and the manufacturer
儀器上面跟那個廠商之間的合作
it becomes as if the communication above
就會變得好像溝通上面
Because this is a very professional kind of astronomy
因為這是很專業的那種天文
Then their kind as far as we know
那他們那種據我們所知的
Probably some heavy industrial equipment
大概都是一些比較重工業儀器的
Between these two, between you and the manufacturer
那這兩個之間你們跟廠商之間
Because it's still about astronomy
因為這還是有關於天文的
the specialized part
那個比較專精的部分
because what you want
因為你們要想到的
communication between them
跟他們之間的溝通上面
does it become
是不是就變成
Can I get a general idea?
可以大概了解一下嘛
That's a good question
這個問題很好就是
Why we need our own engineers
為什麼我們需要我們自己的工程師
just because we need to do it
就是因為我們需要做這件事情
or me too
或者是我自己也是
I want to understand the needs of astronomy
我要了解天文的需求
that understands the norms of astronomy
那了解天文的規範
Then you can communicate with the manufacturer
那你才可以跟廠商溝通說
when i do this now
我現在做這個事情的時候
I don't want to use the traditional way
我不要用傳統的做法
what do i want to change
我要有什麼改變
what do i need
我什麼東西的需求是多少
I didn't talk carefully just now
我剛剛沒有仔細講
In fact, many of our mechanical processing
其實我們很多機械的加工
The accuracy we want is one or two
我們要的精度都是一條或是兩條
That is, its machining accuracy is very, very high.
就是它加工精度就是非常非常的高
One is one-tenth the width of a hair
一條就是十分之頭髮的寬度
So when your team has these concepts
所以當你的團隊有這些概念
And then it itself comes from industry acceptance
然後它本身也來自產業接受
It has a way to go back and communicate with people in this industry
它就有辦法回去跟這個產業的人溝通說
What do I want
我要什麼
Then how can you possibly achieve
然後你怎麼樣可能可以達成
what i want
我要的東西
Just like we developed the Sensor
就像我們開發那個Sensor也是
Because I am the background of Sensor
因為我自己是Sensor的背景
I can communicate with the manufacturer about what I want
我就可以跟廠商溝通說我想要什麼樣的東西
what kind of circuit
什麼樣的電路
this one
這一位
Hello, Dr. Wang, my name is Lin
王博士你好我姓林
i want to ask two questions
我想請問兩個問題
The first is to say that in the development of so-called astronomical instruments
第一個是說在所謂的天文儀器的開發
Not in the development of science graduate instruments
不是科學研究生儀器的開發當中
What disciplines does it really need?
它真正所需要的是哪些學科的人才
Then what is its cultivation and source usually like?
然後它的養成跟來源通常是什麼樣的情況
Then the second question is that in a complete astronomical observation program
然後第二個問題是說在一個完整的天文觀測計畫裡面
The role of the so-called scientist is, for example,
那所謂的科學家的角色就是比如說
astronomer or physicist throughout the program
天文學家或物理學家在整個計畫裡面
What parts of the work does it participate in and what role does it play
它參與的工作是哪些部分跟它扮演的是什麼角色
Thanks
謝謝
we need all kinds of people
我們需要各種不同的人
So in our
所以在我們所裡面
we have optical engineers
我們有光學工程師
we have mechanical engineers
我們有機械工程師
we have microwave engineers
我們有微波工程師
Electronic function engineer Software function engineer
電子功能師 軟體功能師
And the function engineer of the detector
還有偵測器的功能師
So you can basically what I just mentioned
所以你可以 就是基本上我剛剛提到
Each part has a corresponding functional division
每一個部分都有對應的功能師
come and go take care of these things
來去負責這些事情
Because we can't buy anything we touch
因為我們數碰的東西都沒有辦法買得到
I even had to design the circuit myself
我連電路本來我都要自己去設計
Then clean the factory to wash
然後清廠商去洗
Then come back and call yourself like this
然後回來自己喊這樣子
So basically these things are
所以基本上就是這些東西都是
all needed
都是需要的
The second question just said
剛剛第二個問題說
about the role of astronomers in observing
有關於天文學家在觀測的角色
Basically after we finish the instrument
基本上我們做完儀器之後
Astronomers will see that
天文學家就會看到說
There is one more instrument on the earphone side that can be used
光耳機那邊有多了一個儀器可以使用
They are going to explain the characteristics of this instrument
他們就要去了解說這個儀器的特性
We usually do some tests
我們通常會做一些測試
We put the instruments behind the observatory
我們把儀器放到天文台之後
will start testing its basic features
就會開始測試它基本的特性
These properties will have a table
這些特性就會有一個表
or have a system that can do the calculations
或是有一個系統可以去做計算
That day the astronomer based on what he thought
那天文學家根據他想的
he will calculate
他會去計算說
i want to see this celestial body
我要看這個天體
How much observation time may I need
我可能需要多少的觀測時間
Then he will start writing his observation plan.
那就會開始寫他的觀測計畫
the observation program
那觀測計畫
If after the observation time
如果得到觀測時間之後
The weather is great
天氣很好
he gets his information
他就得到他的資料
After getting the information
那得到資料之後
he's going to deal with it
他就要去處理
That deals with the usual words
那處理以通常的話
Every instrument he might have
每一個儀器他可能會有
meeting
會
when we send the instrument out
我們把儀器送出去的時候
we will have
我們會有
Follow his data processing system
跟著他的這個資料處理系統
so he can use
所以他可以用
The data processing systems we provide
我們提供的資料處理系統
to process his data
去處理他的資料
Then do more follow-up analysis
然後做更後續的分析
or
或者是
If he feels that he handles these data
他如果覺得他對這些資料處理
he is sure of himself
他自己很有把握
He can also do his own data processing
他還可以做他自己的這個資料處理
Then do the following analysis
然後來做後面的分析
Then the subsequent analysis may be very
那後面的分析就可能很
there is a big difference
有很大的不同
I may be doing statistics
我可能是做統計
I might just do this for a single celestial body
我可能只是做單一天體的這個
Analysis of characteristics
特性的分析
that makes a big difference
那個就有很大的不一樣
that is
那那個就是
real astronomer
真正的天文學家
or astrophysical systems they
或是天文物理系統他們
they are really professional
他們在真正專業
ok this sir
好 這一位先生
Hello, I am a believer. Let me continue with the question you just answered.
你好 我信仰了 就接著你剛才回答那問題
I want to know, the world is currently full of information to say
我想了解一下 全世界目前是資料多到說
no one to analyze or say this
沒有人去分析 還是說這個
Every astronomer is waiting for that Q to say I want this data
每個天文學家是等著那個Q說我要這個資料
got it a year later
一年之後才拿得到
This is where astronomers have two
這是天文學家有兩種
If you ask our director, he will say that there are too many materials
你會問我們所長 他就會說 資料多了太多
If you go to check it casually, it will be the taper that can produce an infinite amount of taper every year.
你隨便去檢都是那個每年可以出無限多的Taper
In fact, there is a lot of data
其實就是說資料是真的很多
Data that has been observed at various observatories
在各個天文台已經被觀測過的資料
That of course means that there are many problems
那當然就是說有很多的問題
Or there are many specialized subjects
或是有很多專門的課題
It needs new instruments to have a way to break through
是需要新的儀器才有辦法去突破
There is a way to go. For example, I want to see the universe farther away.
才有去辦法 比如說我要看更遠的這個宇宙
Then I couldn't get this far before, I couldn't
那我以前就沒有辦法達到這麼遠 我就沒有辦法
So there are two very different kinds of this
那所以是有兩種非常不同的這個
The path of research looks like this
研究的這個路徑這樣子
right
對
Are there any special requirements for the material of the lens?
那那個透鏡的材質有特別的要求嗎
Is the radius of that area ground by yourself?
那那個區域半徑是自己磨嗎
Well
呃
In most of the development of astronomical instruments
在大部分做天文儀器開發的
The research unit does not grind the lens itself
研究單位是沒有自己磨透鏡
few have
少數有
In fact, we rely a lot on
那其實我們就仰賴很大
These relatively specialized optical manufacturers
這些比較專精的這個光學的大廠
For example, there is a quite large factory in France
比如說法國有一個蠻大的廠
Then Japan like Kallang or Nikon
然後日本比如說加冷或是尼康
they are also very useful
他們也是非常用的
those materials
那這些材料
Visible light materials are usually relatively fixed
可見光的材料通常是比較固定
and easier to get
而且比較容易取得
The market for this is huge
用的這個市場很大
the infrared words
那紅外線的話
so it's more difficult for me
所以我就比較困難
The problem I've found that I often run into is saying
我發現我常常遇到的問題就是說
I now need a lens like 30cm
我現在需要比如說30公分的透鏡
But you ask the whole world to tell you
但是你去問全世界都跟你講
no, no one produces
沒有,沒有人生產
Not the lens, just the material
不是透鏡,單單那個材料
There is no such a large material
這麼大的材料就沒有
So then you have to think of other ways to break through
所以那你就要想其他的方法去突破
For example, if I divide a speed of light into
比如說我把一個光速分成
34 light speeds like this
34個光速這樣子
to do different designs
去做不同的設計
Let me ask Mr. Wang first
我先也問一下王老師
Mainland China because about last year I knew they were going to build a 500-meter-diameter one
中國大陸因為大概在去年我知道他們要建了一個直徑500公尺的那個
Yes, I asked at the beginning
對,我一開始有求
Then I know it seems that he is better than the original
那我知道好像他比原來的
It turns out that it seems to be only about 100 or 200
原來這好像大概只有100多還是200
diameter 300
直徑300
Then his main purpose
然後他的那個最主要的那個目的
And that class should be very high
而且那個class應該很高吧
That is, we usually say that the requirements of this mirror are closely related to its wavelength.
就是我們通常說這個鏡面的要求跟他的波長很有關係
This is what I just showed
這個是我剛好秀這個
their big eyes
他們這個很大的天眼
this is 500 meters
這是五百公尺
Then his main thing
那他主要的這個東西
The wavelength of the tube car
管車的波長
The wavelength of this antenna tube car is
這個天線管車的波長是
possibly centimeter-scale waves
可能是公分級的波
electromagnetic waves
的電磁波
Then his request is like
那他的要求跟比如說
we do
我們做
Chihavanibo
赤豪文尼波
or visible light
或者是可見光那個
ask for this
要求這個
The superficial requirements are much worse
表面的要求就差很多
So the wavelength of my surface is directly proportional to
所以我表面的波長直接成正比
So let's say I can see light
所以比如說我可見光
I have superficial progress requirements
我都有表面進度的要求
This is what we call the Nami rating.
就是我們說的耐米等級
maybe a hundred rice
可能是一百耐米
50-resistant rice
五十耐米
That's because the wavelength of my optics is
那因為我的光學的波長是
hundreds of nanometers
幾百耐米
so if i
所以我如果
He is centimeter grade
他這邊是公分等級
So he superficially asked to become Homi
所以他表面要求變成是豪米
Relatively speaking, the difficulty
那相對來說這個難度就
not that high
不是那麼的高
Of course it's because he's big
那當然因為他很大
but this
但是這個
You said you want to make the optics so big
你說要把光學做到這麼大
This is very currently not possible
這是非常目前來說還是不可能
Let me ask you again, how much will it cost to burn?
再問一下這要大概要燒多少錢才能夠
this is okay
這個還好
this is what we say
這是我們說的
that
那個
i was there last week
我上禮拜才在那邊
To him it's actually
對他其實這個
His reason is that the wavelength is very long
他這個因為是那個波長很長
that metal piece on his face
他表面上的那個金屬片
It's full of holes
上面都是很多洞
Because of him, everything you say is true.
因為他你說說全部是真是全部
It's very heavy with a solid piece of metal
實心的金屬片的話他非常重
He said it was full of holes
他說上面全都是洞
full of holes
上面全都是洞
I mean, if we look from the bottom up
我其實我們從底下往上看的話
Nothing seems to be transparent
好像都沒有東西好像是透明的一樣
it's a lot of holes
是上面很多洞
he is whole he is whole he is string
他整個是整個他整個是弦
There are six towers outside
外面有六個那個高塔
His whole string is on it
他整個弦在上面
They develop a new kind of steel wire
他們發展一種新的一種那個鋼絲
can lift it all up
可以把它整個抬起來
The quality of the steel wire is very good
那鋼絲的那個質量非常好
can hold a lot of weight
可以承受很多重量
What bridge is that pig
那是豬什麼大橋
What is it called Hong Kong Pig Harbor?
叫什麼港豬海港
Hong Kong-Macau Bridge
港澳那個大橋
the line hanging above
上面吊的那個線
developed from them
就從他們這邊發展出來
They have body patents
他們有身形專利
that's all
那整個是
hang on
吊在上面
he spent money
他花了錢
i don't know how much it costs
我不知道花多少錢
But after spending money like this
可是他們這種花了錢之後
after covering
蓋好之後
Their tourism business developed to
他們觀光事業發展到
money earned from tourism
觀光事業賺的錢
More money than the telescope he built
比他蓋的望遠鏡錢還多
So he now covers a lot outside
所以他現在外面蓋了很多
the big hotel
高級的那個大旅館
so let's see
所以就讓大家去看
look at you
那看你那邊上
top middle
最中間上方那邊
there is one that can
有個那個可以
There can be a table inside
可以有個台子裡面
you can go up and see
可以就上去看
You can go outside for sightseeing
就觀光可以到外面去看
not below
不能下面
can't go down
不能到下面去
because of our
因為我們那個
our sky school
我們那個天空學校
we can only be below
我們只能在下面
next to that plate
就在那個盤子旁邊
We can't take pictures like this
照相這種照相我們照不到
I take a photo with my phone
我拿著手機照
According to
照
only on that plate
只能照到那個盤子
about a quarter
大概四分之一左右
We can't take such a panorama
這種全景我們那麼照不到
It must be this. I don’t know how they take pictures.
一定要這個不知道他們怎麼照
I remember taking pictures is worth billions of RMB
我記得照相是幾十億人民幣
billions of RMB
幾十億人民幣
at the last meeting
上次開會的時候
classmate
同學
He said he would find a few more to develop tourism
他說他再多找幾個發展觀光業
In astronomy, he can only do specific astronomy
這個在天文上面他只能做特定的天文
So he is not a very broad
所以他不是一個很廣泛性
ok ok sorry
OK 好 對不起
At least solve my confusion
至少解答我的困惑
Because a lot of people are talking about it
因為不少人都討論這個事情
Is there another Mr.
還有沒有這位先生
Hello, Professor Wang, my name is Jin
王教授你好 我姓金
i want to ask
我想請問說
What kind of environment is restricted in our country
我們國內受限的什麼環境
Is it the land spirit or what?
是地靈處還是什麼
Why is that very large observatory
為什麼那種很大型的天文台
are abroad
都是在國外
because of the old dimension
因為有舊維度而言
our care for the environment
我們的關心環境
should not lose to other
應該不會輸給其他
places like nuclear camp
像核營覽之類的地方
i think you just walked outside
我想你剛剛走到外面
you see us rain
你就看到我們氣雨
Extinguish
免滅
So Taiwan's problem is
所以台灣的問題就是
We have typhoon, we have rain, right?
我們有颱風 我們有美雨 對不對
It rains all winter in northern Taiwan
北台灣是整個冬天都在下雨
Then there will be beautiful rain and spring rain
然後有美雨 有春雨
Well, the weather station, we now know it's probably
好 天溫台 我們現在知道大概是在
It's a high mountain, near Yushan
就是高山嘛 玉山附近
There is no way to go to Yushan
那玉山沒有辦法去
Yushan has no way to go up
玉山沒有路可以上去
So some people may say that Yushan may
所以可能有人說玉山可能
The observation conditions are very good
觀測的條件很好
But there's really no way to get there
但是真的沒有辦法到那邊
that so
那所以
in east asia
在東亞
To be honest, there isn't any table with a good temperature
老實說沒有任何一個好的天溫的台子
is east asia
就是東亞
Usually because of this circulation
通常因為這個環流的關係
It's all on this side of the ocean
都是在大洋的這一側
is dry
是乾的
is the Pacific Ocean
就是太平洋
on the right is
右邊是
is dry left is dead
是乾的 左邊是死的
for the Atlantic Ocean
對 大西洋也是
so good weather deck
所以好的天溫台
Hawaii is an exception
那夏威夷是例外
Hawaii because it is in
夏威夷因為是在
It's an island protruding from the middle of the ocean
就是大洋中間突出來一個島
So basically the airflow is very stable
那基本上那個氣流很穩定
Then the clouds are all under the mountain
然後雲都在山的下面
Its mountain is very high, Jade Mountain is still high
它的山很高 玉山還高
So there is no problem above
所以在上面就沒有問題
that's usually good when otherwise
那不然通常好的時候
on the right side of the ocean
就是在大洋的右側
That is, when he melts, there will be
就是他會有融化的時候會有
he doesn't melt well
他不大會融化
But he doesn't have summer when you go
可是他不是有夏天你們去的時候
It was probably zero when I went there in July.
7月去的時候大概也是零度
right
對
He probably asked about the humidity
他大概是問的是濕度的問題
But usually it's pretty dry most of the time
但是通常大部分的時間都是很乾
is our relative humidity
就是我們相對的濕度
the amount of water vapor in the air
就是空氣裡面的水氣的含量
It has a lot to do with temperature
跟溫度有很大的關係
the more you... the higher the temperature
你越...溫度越高的時候
air water content
空氣水的含量
I'm not talking about humidity now
我現在不再講濕度
It is the amount of water in the air
它是整個空氣裡面水的含量
opposite to temperature
跟溫度是相反
This is when the temperature is lower
就是溫度越低的時候這個
less water content
水含量就越少
Okay, is there any speech for today's teacher Wang?
好 有沒有針對於王老師的那個今天的演講
is there any doubt
還有沒有什麼任何疑問的
All right, man, because we still have a few minutes
好 來 這位 因為我們還有幾分鐘時間
that give him the mic thanks
那個 給他麥克風 謝謝
It seems that there is a slide show about when the old Dong
就是好像有一個投影片是說那個老凍的時候
Doesn't that lens follow that
那個鏡頭不是會隨著那個
Yeah
對 對 對
What method is used to comply with this rapid change
那個是用什麼方式去符合這個快速的變動
Is it supposed to be a mechanical way?
是應該不是機械式的方式
it's the mechanical way
它是機械式的方式
It's a mechanical way, yes
是機械式的方式 對
When we make this instrument
我們做這個儀器的時候
It is we have a device called the Wayfram Sensor
它是 我們有一個叫做Wayfram Sensor
that is to say this thing
就是說這個東西
It can detect how my wavefront has changed
它可以去偵測說我的這個波前改變了什麼樣子
Then I was able to control it's drive behind this mirror
然後我就能夠控制它的這個鏡子後面的驅動器
to allow very small changes to the surface of this mirror
讓這個鏡子的表面能夠產生非常微小的變化
Because this mirror is very, very thin
因為這個鏡子是非常非常薄
so it's thin
所以它很薄
The drive won't break when it's moving around behind it
這個驅動器它後面動來動去的時候它不會破掉
Can move hundreds of times per second
每一秒鐘就可以動好幾百次
This is what we call deformable mirror
這個是我們叫做 deformable mirror
This is a special technique
這個是一個特別的技術
No one in Taiwan should be interested in this
台灣應該是沒有人會對這個有興趣
But it can move very fast
但是它就是可以動很快
This thing is actually very interesting
這個東西其實很有趣
It was actually developed from a new war plan.
它其實是新戰計畫發展出來的
Americans in the 1980s
美國人在1980年代
In order to send lasers into outer space to attack artificial satellites
為了要讓雷射打到外太空去攻擊人造衛星
He also needs to fix atmospheric labor
他也要修正大氣勞動
Otherwise, they went out and said that there is no way to pile them up at one point.
不然那個出去說沒有辦法堆在一點
The lasers have to gather at one point to destroy this thing
雷射要聚在一點才有辦法把這東西打掉
So they went to develop the technology
所以他們就去發展這個技術
Then I returned the new battle plan after the end
然後我還新戰計畫結束之後
After hearing about it, he was very happy to say that this thing is very useful.
聽聞一下他就很高興說這個東西很有用
just use it
就拿來用
Yes because in fact it
對 因為其實它
I'm exaggerating
我這樣有點誇張
In fact, its animal range is very small
其實它動物範圍很小
Its animal range is also
它動物範圍也是
Also Neonometer level
也是Neonometer的等級
good obviously natural
好 顯然天然
Astronomy and Natural Physics Research
天文與天然物理研
Natural Physics Research
天然物理研
Institute of Astrophysics
天文物理研就所
It is actually a cross-domain integration
它其實是一個跨領域整合的
Need all aspects
需要各個方面
You say
您說
say hello online
網上說你好
I want to ask something
我想問一些就是
Should be a basic question for you
應該對你來說是基礎的問題
just to make sure
就是我想確認一下
So visible light observations
所以可見光觀測跟
usually at night
就通常都是夜間觀測
So radio observations are
那所以無線電觀測是
Can it be observed day and night?
日夜都可以觀測嗎
Yes, it depends on your wavelength
有 就是看你的波長
That is to say
也就是說
So usually when doing astronomical observations
那所以通常在做天文觀測的時候
Will it observe 24 hours for radio observation?
無線電觀測它就會24小時的觀測嗎
If it is like the mainland
如果是像大陸那個話
It can be
是可以
But it's you when the sun comes
但是就是你如果太陽來的時候
This signal from the sun is still serious
太陽的這個訊號還是很嚴重
so he just said
所以他就是說
His time can be longer
他的時間可以比較長一點
It is radio, for example, the CMT I just mentioned
就是無線電比如說我剛剛講的這CMT
May be normal visible light environment
可能一般可見光環境
It might close at five o'clock.
可能五點就關滿了
They might get six or seven
他們可能可以搞到六七點
So when observing at night
那所以夜間觀測的時候
because I just saw
因為在我剛剛看到
That's why he's using a camera or
就是所以他是用相機或是
It's just receiving light anyway
就是反正就是收光
So he will be like we see with human eyes
所以他會是像我們用人眼看一樣
Just like photography
就是一直收光像攝影
Or is it like we shoot for a long time
還是說也是像我們拍長時間一樣
For example, every ten minutes
比如說十分鐘收一次
rerun once
翻映一次
then another ten minutes
然後再隔十分鐘
We usually just look at
我們通常就是會看
how dark i want to see
我想要看多暗的東西
I do not want
我不想要
If I say I only need ten minutes
我如果說我只要十分鐘
I can see what he wants
就可以看他我要的東西
I don't want to let him lay for fifteen minutes
我也不想要讓他鋪十五分鐘
But it can change his
可是可以改變他的這個
we call integration time
我們叫積分時間
just the time to light up
就收光的時間
i open the door
我開門一打開
Then I let him keep collecting
然後我就讓他一直收收收
until the time i want
收到我要的時間為止
then the shutter closes
然後快門關起來
I read the image
我把影像讀出來
That is to say, in fact
也就是說其實
Each observatory has a certain
各個天文台他們有一定的
want to see something
想要看的東西
so right
所以很對
No, it's an astronomer
沒有耶 就是天文學家
oh oh oh
喔喔喔
It is the observatory. For example, today is me.
就是天文台比如說今天是我
then i want to see
那我想要看
Well, let's say 15 signals
嗯 我們說15等的信號
Then 15 minutes may be fine.
那15等可能一分鐘就好了
that in addition
那另外
So the whole night is just minute by minute
所以整個晚上就一分鐘一分鐘才
Um
嗯
If I have to wait until 15
如果我都要15等
Then I keep sending for a minute
那我就一分鐘一直派
then i may my this one
那我有可能我這一個
I am in this direction and I want to wait for 15
我在這一個方向我要15等
Then I have to wait 20 in the other direction
那我另外方向要20等
then i will
那我就
going to change
就要去改
So I have to do the math in advance
所以我要事先都算好
Good thing I'm in this one
算好說我在這一個
Uh, when the observatory knows this direction
呃 天文台知道這個方向的時候
how long do i have to lay
我要鋪多久的時間
Then go to how long you have the angle to lay
然後走到你有角度要鋪多久的時間
in this way
這樣子
that is to say
那也就是說
if run out
如果用光
visible light telescope
可見光望遠鏡的話
there is no way
就沒有辦法
Observing the galaxy between the sun and the earth in France
在法觀測太陽跟地球之間的星系
is not a galaxy
就是也不是星系
Just like Mercury or something.
就是比如說水星啊什麼的
Uh, of course because the sun and the earth
呃 當然因為太陽跟地球
The earth revolves around the sun
就是地球繞了太陽轉
So what's behind the sun changes
所以太陽背後的東西是會改變的
Right, so that means if you use visible light
對 所以就是說如果用可見光
You can only observe at night, you can only look away
只能夜間觀測就只能看遠離
yes yes but because
對對對 但是因為
The earth revolves around the sun
就是地球繞了太陽公轉
So I can still see in all directions
所以我還是可以看到四面八方的
I think it's a different time of year
我覺得一年不同的時間
I can see the sky in different places
我可以看到不同位置的天空
The sun is not always with the earth
就是太陽不是永遠跟地球
pointing in the same direction
指著同一個方向
Say you are the sun and I am the earth
比如說你是太陽 我是地球
I'm looking at my back now, right?
我現在看我後面對不對
i can see this sky now
我現在可以看到這個天空
Then I arrived three months later I look here
然後我到了三個月以後我看這邊
I can look over there in three months
再三個月以後我可以看那邊
Yes, yes, see again
對對對 再來看看
i mean
我的意思是指
The galaxies between the sun and the earth
太陽跟地球之間的那些星系
oh those stars
喔那些星星啊
Yes, for example, the southern star is very early or very late
對 比如說 南形星就是很早或很晚的時候
there is still a way
還是有辦法
That is, it is at a very small angle from the sun
就是它離太陽的角度很小
but that angle is small
但是那個角度很小
Still big on astronomical scales
對於天文的尺度來講還是很大
we can still see
我們還是看得到
That is, the range usually taken by astronomy is very small.
就是天文通常拍的那個範圍很小
Yes, like the moon
對 比如說月亮
Let's say the moon is 0.5 degrees
我們說月亮是0.5度
0.5 degrees is already a very wide angle for astronomical observation
0.5度對天文觀察來說已經是非常廣角
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
good
好
I think I've tuned myself into a play lock
我覺得我自己調做戲鎖了
I should study astronomy
我應該去念天文了
Okay, it's about 9 o'clock now
好啦 現在已經約略是9點鐘
Then thank you, thank you very much, Mr. Wang, today is very exciting
那謝謝 非常謝謝王老師今天非常精彩
then let's give him a break too
那我們也讓他休息一下
So with our warmest applause
所以我們以最熱烈的掌聲
Thank you Wang Xiaoyu Mr. Wang
謝謝王小宇 王老師
thank you all
謝謝大家
Then I also tell you
然後我也在跟大家說一下
announce
announce一下
that the next speech will be given by
那個下一次的演講是由
this is a plant
這是植物
Illumination and researcher at the Institute of Parasitology
寄生物研究所的照光與研究員
he wants to talk
他要談
The title of his talk was Exploring the Mysteries of Plant Sexual Reproduction
探討的 他的演講的題目是探索植物有性生殖之奧秘
At that time, I hope everyone can participate enthusiastically
那那個時候到時候再希望大家能夠熱烈的參與
thank you all thank you today
謝謝大家 謝謝今天大家
I came here among my king, thank you all
就是在本王當中前來 謝謝大家
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, all the guests, for coming to our popular science lecture today.
謝謝各位來賓今日來參加本院的科普講座
to make the event better
為了使活動更好